字幕
-我叫早恋-
字幕组制作
字幕组招人
有意者联系QQ群
注意加群备注——霍比特人1字幕所得群号
群号：152664903
翻译：我叫早恋
互动QQ：1076155313
注意添加备注——霍比特人1字幕所得QQ号
校对：我叫早恋、雨-NIKI
感谢：碎丶、最是时光摧枯烂朽
版权问题：禁止任何字幕操作行为
霍比特人
我亲爱的佛罗多
你曾经问我 是否已把历险的所有细节告诉你
我只能说过去告诉你的都是事实
但有些部分却未曾详述
我已经老了 佛罗多
已经不再是年轻时的霍比特人了
我想现在该是让你知道…
全部真相的时候了
故事从很久以前开始
在遥远东方的土地上
一个现如今已不复存在的地方
(夏尔）
那里名叫河谷镇
它的集市远近闻名
总有最好的蔬果和渔获
祥和富裕
它坐落于中土世界最伟大的王国前
伊鲁伯
那是山下国王索尔的堡垒
矮人王国中最强盛者
索尔铁腕统治着
他坚信家族命脉会延续不断
因为其子子孙孙
佛罗多啊，你可不知道
伊鲁伯王国依山势而深建
这座堡垒城市之美谓为佳话传奇
王国的珍宝财富深藏于地下
岩石中挖凿出的宝石
岩层中的金脉 像河流般绵延不绝
矮人的手艺无人能及
他们打造出极致的工艺品
镶满钻石及红蓝绿各色各样的宝石
他们越掘越深 直至黑暗之处
他们也在那里找到了它
山之心
至尊钻石（家传宝钻）
索尔将其命名为〝王之珍宝〞
视其为天授王权的象征
举世皆应向他朝拜
包括伟大的精灵国王瑟兰督伊
但和平盛世好景不长
日子逐渐变得辛酸乏味
连国王的至亲也感到不安
索尔无法抑制对金子的渴望
贪婪开始在他心中生长
那是种吞噬心灵的疾病
一旦病入膏肓
厄运接踵而至
首先是自北方传来仿佛是风暴来临的声音
山间的松针在强烈的热风中窸窣，发出撕裂的声响
巴林，吹响警报
出动卫兵，快点
那是什么？
恶龙
那是来自北方的火龙
史矛革来了
那天的攻击伤亡惨重
但史矛革不是要攻城掠地
而是另有企图
龙族向来疯狂爱恋金饰
不
快走
伊鲁伯沦陷了
恶龙只要活着就绝不会放弃宝物
逃命吧
救救我们
瑟兰督伊不愿牺牲族人的性命 来对抗恶龙
精灵族那天并未出手相救
此后亦然
家破国亡
伊鲁伯的矮人们浪迹荒野
曾经骄傲的人民如今低声下气、苟延残喘
年轻的矮人王子打铁维生
在普通农民的村庄干着粗活
他不会忘记 月下山脉里散发的浓烟
树木像火炬般熊熊燃烧
他见过恶龙的烈焰
让城市灰飞烟灭
他不会原谅
也不曾忘记
亲爱的佛罗多 我就在此处露面
出于命运及一位巫师的决定
命中注定我成为故事的一部分
一开始
就如你所能想到的一样
在地里洞穴中住着一个霍比特人
不是那种又脏又湿的臭洞穴
这是一个霍比特人的住穴
有着美食和温暖的壁炉
还有舒适温暖的家中所需的一切
谢谢
这是什么？
私人物品 非请勿动
这个还没完成
完成这个干什么？
用来阅读
这些究竟是什么东西？
聚会邀请信的回复
啊，不会吧，是今天吗？
Ah. Good gracious. ls it today?
他们全都要来
除了塞克维尔巴金斯一家 要求你亲自去邀请
是吗 除非我死了
他们会喜欢那个主意
他们似乎觉得这里藏了金银珠宝
我只有一个珠宝盒，还装不满
闻起来还有食人妖的味道
你现在在做什么？
防范措施
她曾被我抓到偷拿银器
谁？
罗贝拉塞克维尔巴金斯
她把我所有的银汤匙塞口袋里
恐怖的婆娘
你得看好她，在我离…
在我…
在你怎样？
没什么，没事
叔叔 大家开始对你议论纷纷
他们觉得你变得很奇怪
奇怪？
而且孤僻
我孤僻 胡扯
帮我个忙 把这挂到门上
(除参加派对者 非请勿入)
-你觉得他会来吗？
-谁？
甘道夫
恩，会的。他绝不会错过放烟花的机会
你就等着看他的精彩表演吧
也对，那我走了
去哪？
东小森林，我要给他个惊喜
快去吧，你可不要迟到了
他不喜欢别人迟到
我可没迟到过，我一直很准时
我过去的人生正派可敬
从未发生过任何…
出乎意料的事
意外之旅
(六十年前)
早上好
什么意思？
你只是道早安 还是告诉我无论如何今早都很好？
或者是你今早感觉很好？
又或者是你觉得今早是一个很好的开头？
我觉得以上都对
有事要效劳吗？
现在还说不准
我在寻找可以一起冒险的小伙伴
冒险？
我想布里西边的人都不会感兴趣的
又脏又累又不舒服的玩意儿
会害你错过晚餐
早上好啦
没想到我此生竟会像个小贩
被贝拉多娜的儿子用一句〝早上好〞给打发
你说什么？
你越活越回去了 比尔博巴金斯
抱歉 我认识你吗？
你知道我的名号但忘了我的样子 我是甘道夫
甘道夫是…？
我
甘道夫？你不会是那个浪迹天涯的巫师烟火高手，甘道夫吧？
老图克以前在夏至时都会放它们
没想到你还在营业
不然我还能干嘛？
不然你还能…
很高兴你还记得我
虽然只是关于我的烟火
好，就这么决定了
这对你会很好
对我也会很有趣
我去通知其他人
什么？通知谁？不，不，等一下
这里不欢迎冒险，今天不行
我建议你去小丘或小河那里问问
早上好
德瓦林，听候您的差遣
比尔博巴金斯，听您差遣
我们认识吗？
不认识
在哪边？小兄弟，这边吗？
什么在哪边？
晚餐
他说会有食物，而且很多
他说？谁说的？
这个很好吃，还有吗？
什么？额，哦，有的
请自便
只是我没想到会有访客
门铃声
巴林，任您差遣
晚上好
对，是很好
虽然我觉得会下雨
我迟到了吗？
什么迟到？
晚上好，兄弟
老天，你比上次见时更胖更矮了
只有更胖，没有更矮
脑袋瓜还是比你灵光
对不起，抱歉，我无意打扰
但你们是不是找错地方了
你吃过了吗？
不是我不好客，霍比特人都很好客
只是我希望先认识我的客人
-这是啥？
-我不知道
-乳酪吧，可是变蓝了
-里面长满霉菌
事实上，我根本不认识你们
我不想失礼，但我必须说
对不起
我接受你的道歉
快帮我斟满酒，别小气
-想吃吗？
-如果你坚持的话，我可以再陪你吃点
-菲力
-和奇力
听候您差遣
你一定是伯基斯先生
找错人了，你们不能进来
-你们找错地方了
-什么？
-计划取消了吗？
-没人通知我们
-不，没有取消
-谢天谢地
小心点，我才刚请人磨过
-这地方真不错
-菲力：是很不错
-这屋子是你自己盖的？
-不，是我们家的祖宅
别乱踏，那是我妈的宝箱
菲力、奇力，快来帮忙
德瓦林先生，哈，哈
把这个放到走廊，这样大家都才能进得来
-“大家”？到底有几个人要来？
-要放哪？
-啊，不
-这个真重！
-不行，没人在家
快走开，去烦别人
这里已经有太多矮人
到底是哪个蠢货想出来的玩笑
实在是太没品了
快起来，死胖子
甘道夫
那是我的…别碰我的酒
放回去，给我放回去
别碰我的果酱，不好意思
太扯了吧，你要乳酪刀吗？
要刀干嘛？他都整块吃的
那是蒙戈祖父的椅子 这也是，快放回去
-你说什么？
-那是古董，不是用来坐的
那是书，不是杯垫，把地图放回去
抱歉，甘道夫先生
什么事？
您要来杯甘菊茶吗？
不用，谢谢朵力，给我来点红酒就行了
小心点
是的
菲力、奇力
欧音、葛罗音
德瓦林、巴林、毕佛、波佛 庞伯、朵力、诺力、欧力
别碰我的获奖得来的农作物，多谢
（矮人语）
对，你说对了，毕佛
我们少了一个矮人
他只是迟到而已 他参加完北方宗族聚会就会赶到
甘道夫先生，您要的小杯红酒
果香味很浓
干杯
开始吧，庞伯在吃第二只羊腿了
不可能，太远了
要打赌吗？
庞伯，接住
我来帮你
乱跑的笨蛋
谁要麦酒？拿去
这里，兄弟
我说再喝一杯，给你
数到三
一、二
干杯
我就知道你可以
抱歉，那是桌巾，不是抹布
可是上面很多洞
本来就长这样，是用钩针编的
织那个很好玩，真男人才会爱
这些该死的矮人
比尔博，干嘛这么生气？
干嘛生气？因为被矮人包围 他们在我家干嘛？
一旦习惯后，就觉得他们还挺好玩的
我不想习惯
你看我的厨房，地毯上都是泥
食物柜也被扫空
更别说浴室变成什么鬼样了
水管整个毁了。
我都不知道他们到底在我家干嘛？
抱歉
抱歉，我插下嘴，但盘子该怎么处理？
这里，欧力，把盘子给我
给你
拜托，那是我妈的古董瓷器
超过百年的
拜托不要那样，会把它们弄钝的
你们听到了吗？兄弟
他说刀子会被我们弄钝
磨钝刀子、折弯叉子
打烂瓶子、烧掉塞子
弄破杯子、打碎盘子
比尔博巴金斯最恨这样
割碎桌布、乱丢奶油
卧室地毯留下骨头
还把牛奶洒在地板
再用酒泼每个门板
全都丢进大锅煮汤
用棍猛敲来出气
敲完若有完整容器
就把它们滚到客厅
比尔博巴金斯最恨这样
比尔博
他来了
甘道夫
你不是说这里很好找？
我迷路了两次
要不是门上的记号根本找不到
门上没记号，我一周前才漆过
记号是我做的
比尔博巴金斯，容我介绍此次领队
索林橡木盾
所以
就是这个霍比特人
巴金斯先生，你有战斗经验吗？
-什么？
-斧头还是刀剑？
你拿手的武器是什么？
我还满擅长使用板栗的
但我不了解这有什么关系
我想也是
他不像飞贼，倒像杂货店老板
伊瑞德隆的聚会如何？ 大家都来了吗？
是的，七个王国的使节都来了
全都来啦
铁丘陵的矮人怎么说？
丹恩会支持我们吗？
他们不会来
他们说这次探险是我们自己的事
你们要去探险？
比尔博，麻烦把这里弄亮点
在遥远东方
翻过山陵与河流
穿过密林和荒地
坐落着一座孤独的山峰
(孤山）
孤山
对，欧音占卜了
先兆说时候到了
有渡乌飞往孤山，像预言中那样
〝当昔日的鸟儿再度飞往伊鲁伯〞
〝怪兽的统治将告终〞
额，什么怪兽？
他们指的是恐怖的史矛革
这世代最巨大残暴的凶兽
会飞的喷火怪物
牙齿利如刀刃
爪子又尖又长
非常喜欢贵重金属
我知道什么是龙
我不怕，我准备好了
我要让它尝尝矮人兵器的厉害
-欧力，好样的
-坐下
就算有大军支援，此行仍凶险难测
况且我们只有十三人
还不是最顶尖的十三个
也不是最聪明的
你在说谁笨啊？
对不起，他说了什么？
或许我们人数不多
但我们都是战士，至死方休
别忘了，我们队里还有一位巫师
甘道夫这辈子一定杀过上百只龙
不，我不会这么说
那是几只？
什么？
你杀过几只龙？
快啊，给我们个数字
拜托
我们看到先兆，别人就看不到吗？
谣言已经开始四散
恶龙史矛革已六十年不见踪影
众人放眼东方孤山，打量着…
思索着，估计着风险
或许我们的财富此刻无人看管
我们该坐视不管任由他们信手拿来吗？
或我们应该趁此机会夺回伊鲁伯？
你忘了件事，正门被封上了
无法进入孤山
巴林，事实上这不完全正确
你是如何拿到的？
是你父亲给我的
索恩
他让我负责看管
现在是你的了
要是有钥匙
就一定有门
据记载，有一条秘密地道通往底层大厅
还有其他方法进去
很难找，矮人门在关闭时是隐形的
答案藏在地图某处，但我无法破解
不过在中土世界有人可以
我计划的任务需要机密行事
和非凡的勇气
如果我们谨慎小心，应该可以成功
所以我们需要一个飞贼
一个厉害的专业飞贼
你是吗？
我是什么？
他说他是专业的
我？不，不，我不是飞贼，我这辈子没偷过东西
恐怕我得同意巴金斯先生的话
他看来不是飞贼的料
对
荒野不适合不能保护自己的温顺良民
他没问题
够了
我说比尔博巴金斯是飞贼 他就是飞贼
霍比特人行动非常敏捷
想要的话，他们可以来去无踪
况且恶龙太熟悉矮人的味道
却从未闻过霍比特人的味道
这让我们占很大优势
你要我找远征队第十四名伙伴
我选择了巴金斯先生
这个霍比特人不可貌相
他的能力会超乎你们的想象
连他自己都不知道
这点你们得相信我
好吧
就依你吧
不
把契约给他
成功，出发
只是一般合约，概述自费的部分
所需时间、酬金、丧葬费用等等
丧葬费用？
我不能保障他的安全
我知道
我也不会为他的命运负责
同意
〝契约：货到付款，如有获利 每人最高可得十四分之一〞
听起来挺公平的
〝团体将不为探险中 引发或导致的伤害负责
其中包括但不局限于撕裂伤
腹腔器官遗失〞
焚烧致死？
它眨眼间就能把你化为灰烬
你没事吧？小兄弟
没事
感觉有点头昏
想象它是有翅膀的焚化炉
我需要空气
电光火石间，灼热之疼，你就化为灰烬
不行
你真会帮倒忙，波佛
我没事，让我静坐一会
你已经静坐太久了
从何时起，你母亲的桌布和瓷器
变得对你如此重要？
我记得年轻的霍比特人在树林里找寻着精灵
总在外面待到很晚，天黑才回家
身上拖着泥巴、树枝和萤火虫
那个小霍比特人一心只想知道
在夏尔外面是一个怎样的世界
这世界不在你的书本和地图之中
它在外面
我不能就这样往外面乱闯
我是在袋底的巴金斯
但你也有图克的血统
你知道你曾曾曾叔祖父-吼板图克
体型高大，他可以骑真正的马吗？
是的
没错，他可以
在绿原之战，他攻击半兽人军队
猛力朝半兽人国王的头挥舞棍棒
把头打飞到一百码外的兔子洞里
赢了战争
也因此发明高尔夫游戏
我知道那是你瞎编的
所有的好故事都值得锦上添花
你回来后也会有几个故事可说
你能保证我会回来吗？
不能
如果你能回来
就会和以前不同
我想也是
抱歉，甘道夫，我不能签
你找错霍比特人了
看来我们的飞贼跑了
这样也好
局势本来就对我们不利
我们只是群乌合之众
商人、矿工
焊锅匠、玩具师傅
不是传奇人物的料
我们之中有几位战士
老战士
我宁愿选你们也不要铁丘陵大军
当我召唤时，你们挺身前来
忠诚、荣誉
和一颗自愿的心
夫复何求
你不必这么做
你有选择
你已为我们的人民尽心尽力
你替我们在蓝山打造了新生活
祥和富足的新生活
胜过伊鲁伯所有的黄金
钥匙从我祖父和父亲传承到我这里
冀望有天伊鲁伯矮人能夺回家园
没有选择，巴林
对我而言没有
那我们支持你，小兄弟
我们来完成这件事
越过冰冷和雾气的山脉
到达地下城池
和古洞里
我们需在
天亮前出发
寻找遗忘已久的美丽黄金所在地
松树在高地哭嚎
强风在夜间喧闹
火焰赤红，无情蔓延
树木像火把般狂啸
有人吗？
太好了
(签名：索恩之子索林 见证人：方丁之子巴林)
(飞贼：)
比尔博先生，你要去哪？
我不能停，迟到了
做什么要迟到了？
我要去探险了
原来我就说来这是浪费时间
一点也没错
真可笑的主意，竟然来找霍比特人
到底是谁的馊主意？
等等
我签了
你看
一切核对无误
欢迎巴金斯少爷
加入索林橡木盾的队伍
给他一匹小马
不用麻烦了
谢谢，我步行也跟得上
我常徒步旅行
有一次还走到蛙村
付钱吧，诺力
还有
谢了，兄弟
那是怎么回事？
他们在赌你会不会来
大部分的人赌你不会
那你怎么想？
这个嘛
亲爱的朋友，我从没怀疑过你
是马毛，我过敏了
糟了，等一下，停
我们得回头
怎么回事？
我忘了带手帕
拿去
用这条
前进
你得习惯没手帕
还有其他东西，比尔博巴金斯
在我们旅程结束前
你出生于夏尔的山丘小河间
但家园现已被抛在身后
而世界正在眼前
你好，乖小马
小桃，这是我们之间的小秘密
别说出去
那是什么？
半兽人
半兽人？
割喉者，至少有几十人
野地里到处都是
趁半夜大家熟睡时出击
又快又准，无声无息，只留血迹
很好笑吗？
你们认为半兽人的夜袭是笑话？
我们没那个意思
没错
你们对世界一无所知
别介意，小兄弟
索林痛恨半兽人是大有原因的
在恶龙占领孤山后
索尔国王试图夺回矮人王国摩瑞亚
但敌人抢先一步到达
摩瑞亚已遭大军攻下
由最恐怖的半兽人带头
毁灭者阿索格
巨大的刚达恶半兽人
誓言要断绝都灵的血脉
他决定…
从斩首国王开始
不
索恩，也就是索林的父亲，悲伤得发狂
他失踪了，不知是被杀还是被俘
我们群龙无首
溃不成军
落败和死亡笼罩我们
那时我看到他
年轻的矮人王子
与苍白的半兽人决一死战
独自面对恐怖的敌人
他穿着破裂的盔甲
捡起橡木枝干抵挡攻击
毁灭者阿索格那天上了一课
都灵的血脉绝不会轻易断绝
我们重整旗鼓
击退半兽人
我们的敌人
被打败了
但那晚并没庆功宴
也没高歌
因为死伤惨重，令人悲痛
只有我们几个幸存
我那时暗自思索
我愿意追随这个人
我愿意
称他为王
那个苍白的半兽人
后来怎么了？
滚回了他的洞穴
早就因重伤而死了
(通知主人)
(我们找到那些矮杂碎了)
甘道夫先生 阻止大水好么？
这是在下雨，矮人先生
下完自然就会停
你想改变天气，得找其他巫师
-还有其他的吗？
-什么？
其他的巫师
总共有五位
地位最高的是白袍巫师萨鲁曼
另外还有两位蓝袍巫师
不过我忘了他们的名字
那第五位是谁？
是褐袍巫师瑞达加斯特
他很厉害吗？还是像你一样？
我觉得他是位特立独行的巫师
个性温和，情愿与森林动物为伍
他看管东边的广大森林
幸好有他
因为邪恶总是在寻觅立足之地
不好了，大事不好了
不，萨巴斯汀
老天
快
退后，给它点空间呼吸
我不知道为什么没用
这又不是邪恶巫术
邪恶巫术
没错，这就是
黑暗又强大的巫术
那些恐怖的怪物是从哪来的？
旧堡垒？
带我去看
我们今晚在这里扎营
菲力、奇力，你们负责照顾这些小马 待在它们身边
这里曾经住过农夫一家人
欧音、葛罗音，你们负责升火
没问题
我认为最好继续前进
可以继续往山谷前进
我跟你说过
我不会靠近那个地方
为什么？精灵会帮助我们
我们可以获得食宿和建议
我不需要他们的建言
爱隆王可以帮我们解读那张地图
帮我们？
恶龙攻击伊鲁伯时
精灵帮过我们吗？
半兽人掠夺摩瑞亚
亵渎我们的圣殿
精灵依旧冷眼旁观
你竟要我去求背弃我祖父
背弃我父亲的人
你不是他们
给你地图钥匙，不是要你记着旧恨
你也无权留着它们
一切都还好吧？
甘道夫，你要去哪里？
去找队伍中唯一有理性的人
是谁？
我自己，巴金斯先生
我今天受够矮人了
来吧，庞伯，我们饿了
他会回来吗？
他去好久了
-谁？
-甘道夫
他是巫师，总是我行我素
来，帮个忙，拿去给大家
不行，你吃很多了
庞伯，炖肉比你想象中的好吃
朵力也会煮
真爱说笑
怎么了？
我们应该看着小马
可是出了一点小状况
本来有十六匹马
现在只剩十四匹
黛西和邦果不见了
这不太妙
糟糕透顶，不告诉索林吗？
不，别让他担心
-身为我们的飞贼，或许你该去调查
-饿，这个...
看，有大东西把树连根拔出来了
我们也是这么想
很大，而且可能很危险的东西
看
有灯火
过来
蹲低点
那是什么？
食人妖
他抓了小桃跟薄荷
他们要把马吃了，我们得想办法
是的，你该想办法
你个儿小，他们又慢又笨看不到你
没事的，我们在后面罩你
若真有事，就学仓鸮叫两声 再学褐鸮叫一声
仓鸮叫两声，还是褐鸮叫两声…
你们确定这是好主意？
昨天吃羊肉，今天吃羊肉
看来明天也会吃羊肉
别抱怨了
这些不是羊，是新鲜的马肉
我从来就不喜欢马，肉不够肥
总比又干又硬的农夫好
全是皮包骨，我到现在还要剔牙
好极了，谢谢你替我们加料
可能味道会好吃一点
你要我还有很多
别再来了
坐下
你最好把内脏给除掉
我不喜欢臭兮兮的部分
我说坐下
我饿死了
我们今晚到底吃不吃马？
闭嘴，我给你啥你就吃啥
为啥他煮饭？每道菜吃起来都一样
全都吃起来像鸡肉
除了鸡肉以外
鸡肉吃起来像鱼
我只是就事论事，你们该心怀感激
〝多谢你，真好吃，伯特〞
那有多难？
再加点松鼠屎调味
等等，那是我的酒
抱歉
味道真是恰到好处
用你的鸟嘴尝尝看
好吃吧？
所以我才是大厨
我快饿死了，得吃点东西
肉，我要吃肉
老天
伯特，你看我擤出什么
四肢都很齐全
这是啥？
不知道，但我不喜欢他乱扭的样子
你是啥？超大号松鼠吗？
我是飞贼…霍比特人
飞贼霍比特人？
可以把他煮了吗？
可以试试
他只够一口的份量
尤其是剥皮去骨后
或许这附近有更多飞贼霍比特人
或许足够烤一个派
-抓住他 -他动作太快了
过来，你这个…
抓到了
附近还有你的小同类吗？
没有
他在说谎
我没有
烤他的脚趾
逼他招供
放下他
你说啥？
我说…
放下他
拿袋子来，把他们装起来
快点，快起来
-比尔博 -不
把武器放下
不然我们就把他撕碎
好烫，救命，好烫
别费心煮熟他们
把他们压成肉酱就行了
可以洒上鼠尾草再煎烤一下
有必要这样吗？
听起来挺好的
-把我解开，先生 -去吃跟你一样大的家伙
别管调味料，我们没时间了
就快黎明了，我们动作快点
我可不想变成石头
等等
你们犯下大错了
你无法跟他们讲理，他们是笨蛋
如果他们是笨蛋，那我们是什么？
我是说调味料
调味料怎么了？
你闻过他们吗？
要用比鼠尾草更香的东西才能入口
-叛徒 -你哪懂怎么煮矮人？
闭嘴
让飞贼霍比特人说话
烹煮矮人的秘诀是…
是啥？快告诉我们秘诀
好，我告诉你，秘诀是…
要先剥皮
什么？剥皮？
汤姆，把剥皮刀给我
我要剥了你的皮，你这个…
我不会忘记这笔帐的
你乱讲
我以前常连皮吃
连衣服鞋子都吞下去
他说得对
矮人生吃也很好
又香又脆
那个不行，他有病
-有啥？ -对，他的肠子里有虫
事实上他们都有
他们都有寄生虫，真的很可怕 是我就不会冒这个险
他是说寄生虫吗？
我们才没有寄生虫，是你吧？
你在胡说什么？
我的寄生虫跟手臂一样粗
我的寄生虫是最大只的
-我们病了 -对，我病了
我们都病得很厉害
那你要我们怎么做？
放他们走吗？
-这个嘛… -你以为我不知道你想干嘛？
这个小雪貂想耍我们
-雪貂？ -耍我们？
让黎明收服你们
-那是谁？ -不知道
他可以吃吗？
把你的脚从我背上移开
你去哪了？
去前头探路
你为何回来？
回头打探一下
千钧一发
所幸大家都没事
你的飞贼一点都帮不上忙
他懂得拖延时间
你们其他人都没想到这点
他们一定是从伊顿荒原来的
食人妖何时开始往远处游荡了
已经一个世纪多不曾这样
自从黑暗统治这些土地以后就不这样了
他们不可能白天行动
表示附近一定有山洞
什么这么臭？
这是食人妖藏宝窟
小心不要乱碰
这样随地乱放真是可惜
-谁都可以拿走 -我同意
-诺力 -干嘛？
拿把铲子
这些剑不是出自食人妖之手
也不是人类工匠打造
这是第一纪元高等精灵
在贡多林铸造的
再也找不到更好的剑了
-放进去 -很好
好，来，快点
我们在做长期储蓄
我们离开这个污秽之地
来吧，走了
波佛、葛罗音、诺力
比尔博
给你
这个尺寸适合你
我不能收
这把短剑是精灵做的
当半兽人接近时会闪耀蓝光
我这辈子从没用过刀剑
我希望你永远用不上
但当派上用场时，请记得
真正的勇气不在于知道什么时候取人性命
而在于什么时候饶恕性命
有东西接近
-甘道夫 -大家别散开
快点，武装自己
小偷、火、杀人犯
瑞达加斯特？
是褐袍瑞达加斯特
话说…
你怎么会在这里？
我在找你，甘道夫
大事不好了
大事非常不好
怎么说？
给我一分钟想想
我刚才想到就忘了
话明明已经到了舌尖
那不是话
那是一只…
竹节虫
绿森林生病了，甘道夫
黑暗笼罩大地
万物停止生长
只长出坏东西
空气弥漫着腐臭
最糟糕的是那些网
网？什么意思？
蜘蛛，甘道夫，很大的那种
肯定是昂哥立安的后代 不然我就不是巫师
我跟踪它们
它们来自多尔哥多
多尔哥多
那个老堡垒早就荒废了
不，甘道夫
没荒废
黑暗的力量盘据在那里
前所未见的黑暗力量
上古的恐怖黑影
这股力量能够召唤…
亡灵
我亲眼看到，甘道夫
从黑暗中
窜出一个死灵法师
瑞达加斯特
快点，快点
等等
对不起
来口老托比烟草
帮你安定心神
吐气
现在，你确定是死灵法师？
这绝非来自阳界
是狼嚎吗？这里有狼吗？
不，那不是狼
奇力，快准备好弓箭
座狼探子
也就是半兽人大军就在附近  半兽人大军？
除了族人，你跟谁提过远征的事
没有别人
-你跟谁提过？ -我发誓没有别人
到底发生什么事？
你们在被猎杀
我们得离开此处
没办法，我们没有小马
它们跑了
我去引开它们
那些是刚达巴座狼，它们会追上你
这些是罗斯加堡兔子
鹿死谁手还很难说
来吧
来抓我啊
走
别走散
快跟上
欧力，不，退后
全部人，都跟上，快点
你要带我们去哪？
(矮杂碎在那里)
(快去追)
前进，快点
他们在那里
往这边，快点
更多敌人杀来了
奇力
射他们
我们被包围了
甘道夫呢？
他抛下我们了
守住阵地
往这边走，傻瓜
快点
快点，你们所有人
快
走…
八、九、十
奇力！快跑！
精灵
看不到通道通哪去，要走吗？
当然要走
这才是明智之举
来吧，兄弟
伊姆拉崔河谷
也就是一般人口中常说的…
瑞文戴尔
此处是东方大海的最后庇护所
你一直盘算引我们来此
向我们的敌人寻求庇护
你在这里没有敌人，索林橡木盾
河谷中唯一的敌意来自你
你认为精灵会为我们的远征祈福？
他们会试图阻止我们
那是当然，但我们有问题需要解答
此事要成功，需要用到手腕和
尊敬
还有迷人的魄力
所以由我来负责交涉
米斯兰达
林德
小心点
(我们听说您进入了河谷)
我得跟爱隆王谈谈
爱隆王不在这里
不在这里？
那他在哪？
集合备战
-甘道夫 -爱隆王
(我的朋友)
(你去哪了？)
(我们去猎捕来自南方的半兽人军队)
(在秘密通道附近杀了几个)
半兽人竟然敢靠近我们的边界
某事或某人必然吸引了他们
有可能是我们
欢迎你，索林，索恩之子
我想我们没见过
你长得像你祖父
我认识索尔时，他还是山下国王
是吗？他从未提过你
他在说什么？
他在出言侮辱我们吗？
不，葛罗音先生，他想请你们吃饭
这样的话，就请带路吧
来嘛，试一口
我不喜欢绿色食物
肉在哪里？
他们有薯片吗？
谢谢你邀请我们
我的服装不适合晚宴
你向来如此
这是兽咬剑，斩杀半兽人的名剑
此剑…
是我西方高等精灵宗族所铸造
希望对你大有助益
而这是格兰瑞
是贡多林国王的敌击剑
是第一纪元与半兽人交战时…
别费心了，小兄弟 刀剑因为在战争中的功绩得名
你是说我的剑从未上过战场？
那不太像是一把剑
比较像拆信刀
你是如何取得的？
在东方大道上的食人妖洞穴
就在遭遇半兽人突袭前
你们怎么会在东方大道上？
我们的事无须精灵来管
老天，索林，把地图给他看
这是我人民的遗产
其中的秘密由我来保护
我快被矮人的固执烦死了
你的骄傲有天会害了你
你站在中土世界少数能解读地图的人面前
快给爱隆王看
索林，不要
伊鲁伯？
你为何对这地图感兴趣？
主要是学术研究
如你所知，这类古物通常藏有密语
你还会读古矮人语，对吗？
月古文字
月古文字？
那是当然
很容易就被忽略
看来是没错 月之文字只能透过月光读取
月亮的季节和形状要和书写时一致
你能读吗？
这些符文是在夏至傍晚所写
约在两百年前的新月月光下
看来你们是注定来到瑞文戴尔
命运眷顾着你，索林橡木盾
同样的月光，今晚将照耀你我
〝当画眉鸟敲打的时候 站在灰色的岩石旁边〞
〝落日藉着都灵之日的余晖〞
〝将会照耀在钥匙孔上〞
都灵之日？
从矮人新年的元旦开始，当秋天末月和冬日初阳同时在空中交会
这是坏消息
夏日将尽，都灵之日就快到了
我们还有时间
-有时间做什么？ -找到入口
我们得在正确时间 站在正确地点上
唯有如此，门才能被打开
所以你们的目的是要入山
那又如何？
有人会觉得此举并不明智
什么意思？
你并不是中土世界唯一的守护者
(那些矮人…主人)
(我们追丢了)
(我们被污秽的精灵突袭)
(我不要听藉口)
(我要矮人国王的头颅)
(我们寡不敌众)
(无计可施)
(我好不容易才死里逃生)
(让你活着…)
(只是浪费)
(矮人很快就会现身)
(通知大家)
(悬赏他们的人头)
不，你做了同样的事 又不是没做
朵力，来，拿着
庞伯
不管我们帮不帮忙 矮人都会前进孤山
他们决意要收复失土
索林橡木盾觉得 他不需向任何人解释
我也不觉得
你需要解释的对象不是我
凯兰崔尔女王
米斯兰达
(好久不见)
(时间改变了我)
(却没有改变罗瑞安女皇)
我不知道爱隆王通知了您
不是他
是我
萨鲁曼
你最近很忙啊，我的朋友
告诉我，甘道夫
你真以为你的计谋不会被发现？
不被发现？
不
我只是凭良心办事
恶龙困扰你很久了
这是实话，女王
史矛革不听命于任何人
但它若与敌人结盟
将会造成巨大伤害
什么敌人？
甘道夫，敌人早已溃散
索伦已被击败，法力永远无法恢复
甘道夫，我们已经承平了四百年
一个得来不易，戒慎恐惧的和平
是吗？我们有和平吗？
食人妖下山来作乱
他们掠夺村庄，摧毁农田
半兽人在半路上攻击我们
这也不算是战争的先兆
你总爱小题大作
无事庸人自扰
让他继续说
除了史矛革外，还有其他危机
比它更强大的力量
我们可以视而不见，但却无法偏安
绿森林里邪病丛生
居民现在称它为幽暗密林
他们说…
怎么了？你接着说啊
告诉我们居民说了什么
他们说有死灵法师住在多尔哥多
一个可以召唤亡魂的巫师
这太荒谬了
这种力量不存在世界上
这个死灵法师只是凡人
一个爱操弄黑魔法的魔术师
我本来也是这么想
-但瑞达加斯特看到… -瑞达加斯特
别跟我提那个褐袍巫师瑞达加斯特
他是个蠢材
他的确特立独行，离群索居
不只这样，他是毒蘑菇吃多了
浑沌了他的心智，染黄了他的牙齿
我警告过他
埃斯塔力一族不该在森林游荡
你带着某物
是瑞达加斯特给你的
他在多尔哥多找到此物
是的
给我看看
他根本没在听，我算是在自言自语
那是什么？
是魔多的遗物
魔窟剑
为安格马的巫王专门铸造
也随他而下葬
当安格马被攻破时
北方民族将他的尸首和所有物品
封印在鲁道尔荒陵上
他们将之深埋石堆
墓地如此黑暗
永不见天日
这是不可能的
墓地被封上强大的咒语
不可能被破解
如何证明此剑来自安格马墓穴？
无法证明
因为没有证据
我们来检视一下已知的事实
一小群半兽人
胆敢跨越布鲁南
有人寻获一把古老匕首
有凡人魔法师自称是死灵法师
并住在荒废堡垒中
这都不是什么大不了的事
但矮人远征队的事很困扰我
我不同意，甘道夫
我无法赞同这次远征
他们早点请示我 就不用失望折返了
我不懂你为何要燃起他们的希望
他们要离开了
是的
你知道
他们也只能接受了
爱隆王
矮人们已自行离开了
小心前进
我们将越过荒野的边缘
巴林，这些路你熟，你带头
好
巴金斯先生
我建议你跟上队伍
你会跟随他们？
是的
你帮助索林橡木盾是对的
我只担心这个远征队会引出…
我们尚不了解的力量
一定要解开魔窟剑之谜
有事在暗中行动，躲过我们的耳目
不愿露出真面目
时候还未到
但它的力量日益茁壮
切记，你一定要小心
米斯兰达
为何选择半身人？
我也不知道
萨鲁曼认为，这是能抵抗邪恶的
唯一强大力量…
但我发现的却并非如此
我发现细微的事物
普通人坚持不懈的行动能抑制邪恶
简单的行为，像是慈善和爱
之所以选择比尔博巴金斯
或许是因为我害怕
而他让我勇敢
别害怕，米斯兰达
你并不孤单
(若你需要我的帮助)
(我定会前来)
慢慢来，小心走
比尔博
我们得找个地方躲雨
注意
小心，兄弟
抓好了
这不是什么暴风雨
根本就是雷暴
快看
我的天啊
传说是真的
是巨人，石巨人
快找掩护，笨蛋
抓稳了
-怎么回事？ -抓住我的手
快走
快点，跳过去
小心
-兄弟 -快跳
来啊
抓稳了
不
不，奇力
没事，他们还活着
比尔博呢？霍比特人去哪了？
在那里
快救他
-抓住我的手 -比尔博
-欧力，小心 -抓着
我抓住你了，兄弟
抓好，抓好
来，兄弟，快上来
我还以为我们失去飞贼了
他离开家的那刻就走丢了
他不该来的
他不属于我们的团体
德瓦林
看起来算安全
去后面看看
山洞通常都有东西居住
这里空空如也
好，我们来升火
不，别在这里升火
去睡吧
我们黎明就动身
我们该在山里等甘道夫会合
本来计划如此
计划改变
波佛，你值第一更班
(气味还很新鲜)
(他们走了山路)
你要去哪？
回瑞文戴尔
不，你现在不能回头
你是我们远征队的一分子
可是我格格不入
索林说我不该来的，他说得没错
我不是图克，我是巴金斯 我都不知道当时我是怎么想的
我不该冲出家门的
我心里明白，其实你是想家了
不，你们都不明白
你们是矮人，习惯这种生活
到处旅行，四处漂泊，没有归属
对不起，我不是有意…
对，你说得没错
我们是没有归属的
祝你万事顺利
我是真心的
那是什么？
醒来，快醒来
小心
滚开
你这肮脏的怪物
退下！
你找死
好了，别推了
把你的脏手从我身上拿开
别碰我
离他远一点
竟然敢全副武装地闯入我的王国
是间谍？小偷？还是刺客？
是矮人，凶狠的大王陛下
矮人？
我们在前廊找到他们
还站着干嘛，快搜身
每个口袋都别放过
你们所为何来？
快说
好吧
不肯说是吧，我们就逼他们说
把绞肉机和碎骨机拿来
-从最年轻的开始下手 -等等
哎，呦，喂
看看是谁来了
索林，索恩之子，索尔之子
山中国王
哦，呵呵，不好意思，可能我老糊涂了，你没有山
你也不是什么国王
不就是个无名小卒而已
我知道有人出高价悬赏你的人头
只要头
身体就免了
你应该知道我在说谁
你的老敌人
苍白的半兽人，骑着白座狼
毁灭者阿索格已经死了
很久前就在战场上被杀了
所以，你就以为他不会再毁灭了吗？
传话给苍白半兽人
告诉他，我中大奖了
好耶
好极了
咕鲁，咕鲁
肮脏的半兽人
多骨少肉，宝贝
但聊胜于无
好多骨头，宝贝，好少肉
闭嘴，快点剥皮
从头开始
寒气冰冰，刺疼手心
咬着脚底
巨岩和石块好像骨骸
无肉无依
冰冷死尸，了无气息
美味爽口
感谢保佑，小宝贝
这个看起来肉很多
咕鲁，咕鲁
退后，退后
我警告你，别再靠近
他有精灵的剑，但他不是精灵
他不是精灵
那他是什么？小宝贝
他是什么？
我叫比尔博巴金斯
巴金斯？
什么是巴金斯？小宝贝
我是来自夏尔的霍比特人
我们喜欢半兽人、蝙蝠和鱼 但从没试过霍比特人
肉质肥美多汁吗？
请你保持距离
不然我要用剑了
我不想惹麻烦，懂吗？
告诉我怎么出去，我就走
怎么？你迷路了？
对，我想尽快找到出路
我们知道霍比特人的安全路线
在黑暗中的安全路线
闭嘴
-我什么也没说 -我们不是在跟你说话
是的，宝贝，我们是的
我不知道你在玩什么游戏
游戏？
我们最喜欢游戏了，宝贝
你喜欢游戏吗？想玩吗？
或许吧
什么有脚却无人知晓
高大胜过树木
耸立直入云霄
却永远不会长高？
-是山 -对，对
再玩一个吧
再一个，快来考我们
不，不要再玩猜谜了
杀了他，杀了他
咕鲁，咕鲁
不，不
不，我想玩，我很想
我想玩，我看得出来…
你很会猜谜
所以我们何不…
玩猜谜游戏？
就我们俩
好，好，就我们俩
好，好
如果我赢了
你告诉我怎么出去，好吗？
好，好
那如果你输了怎么办？
如果他输了，宝贝，就吃掉他
如果巴金斯输了，我们要一口吃掉
很公平
那巴金斯先来
三十匹白马站在红色山丘上
它们先大嚼特嚼，然后用力跺脚
最后就伫立不摇
是牙齿吗？
牙齿
太好了，我的宝贝
但我们…只有九颗
换我们了
无声却会哭
无翼却会飞
无牙却会咬
无嗓却会呢喃
等等
我们知道，我们知道
闭嘴
是风
是风，当然是风
非常聪明，霍比特人
非常聪明
盒子没有盖子、锁孔和绞链
但里面却藏有金黄色的宝藏
盒子
盒子，盖子和锁孔
答案呢？
真难
盒子，锁孔
你放弃了吗？
给我们一个机会，宝贝
蛋
是蛋
又湿又脆的蛋，是的
祖母教我们要吸蛋，是的
我们也有一题
它会吞食一切
虫鱼鸟兽花草树木
咬破生铁，蚀穿金钢
将岩石化成飞灰
回答我们
让我想想，刚才你也想很久
鸟兽
兽？花树…
我不知道这题
他好吃吗？
他可口吗？
他酥脆吗？
让我想想
让我想一想
他卡住了
巴金斯卡住了
时间到
时间
答案就是时间
其实没有很难
最后一题
最后机会
好
问我们
-问我们 -好，我要问了
我口袋里放了什么？
不公平
这不公平，违反游戏规则
问我们其他问题
不，不，不
你叫我问问题，这就是我的问题
我口袋里放了什么？
猜三次，宝贝，得让我们猜三次
猜三次，没问题，猜吧
是手
错，继续猜
鱼骨、半兽人、牙齿 贝壳、蝙蝠翅膀
小刀
闭嘴
又错了，最后一次机会
线头
还是什么都没有
一次猜两个，以上皆错
所以…
我赢了，你答应过带我出去
宝贝，我们答应过吗？
我们这样说过吗？
他口袋里放了什么？
那不关你的事
你输了
输了？
在哪里？
不
不，不
掉了
诅咒我们，杀了我们吧
我的宝贝丢了
你丢了什么？
别问我们，不关他的事
不
咕鲁，咕鲁
他肮脏的小口袋里
到底…
放了什么？
被他偷了
骨头被打断，脖子被扭断
毒打完后再痛殴，然后吊到绞架
死在地底未知处
葬身在这半兽城
我认得那把斩杀半兽人的名剑
那把咬剑
砍断了上千个半兽人的脖子
砍死他们，打死他们，动手
把他们全杀了
砍掉他的头
捡起兵器
战斗
他拿的是敌击剑，打剑
如阳光一般刺眼
索林
跟我来，快点
快跑
还给我们
那是我们的
小偷
巴金斯
赶紧走
快点
用木桩
冲啊
砍断绳索
快点
-动作快 -庞伯
快走…
跳过去
跳啊
快走
推啊
快点
小心后面
你以为你逃得过我
你无计可施了吧？巫师
用这招也行
还不算太糟
胡说
你是在开玩笑吧
甘道夫
他们人数众多，我们不是对手
唯一能救我们的只有日光
快跑
快站起来
-巴林 -来啊
等等
我的宝贝，等等
咕鲁，咕鲁
快点
这边
加油，快点
很好
巴金斯
小偷
我们诅咒你，我们永远恨你
五、六、七、八
毕佛、波佛，十个了
菲力、奇力，十二个了
加上庞伯十三个
比尔博在哪？
我们的霍比特人呢？
该死的半身人，现在他走丢了
我以为他跟朵力一起
-别怪我 -你最后在哪看到他？
第一次被抓时 他趁机溜了
然后发生什么事 告诉我
让我来告诉你
巴金斯看到机会就溜之大吉
他离家后就只想着软床和壁炉
我们不会再见到那个霍比特人
他早就走了
不
他没有
比尔博巴金斯
你是我这辈子最高兴看到的人
比尔博 还以为见不到你了
你是怎么逃过半兽人的？
你怎么出来的？
那不重要 他回来了
当然重要 我想知道
你为什么回来？
我知道你一直对我感到质疑
你说得对 我很想念袋底洞
我想念我的书
我的椅子还有花园
那是我的归属
我的家
所以我回来 因为…
你们没有家
你们的被夺走了
我愿意帮你们拿回来
(去追他们)
(把他们杀了)
真是一波未平
一波又起，跑
快跑
快
爬到树上
全部上去，比尔博，快点
赶快
他们来了
-撑着 -抓好，兄弟们
阿索格
(闻到了吗？)
(恐惧的气味)
(我记得你父亲身上恐惧的臭味)
(索林，索恩之子)
不可能
(那个矮人是我的)
(其他人全杀掉)
(喝他们的血)
要倒了
菲力
好耶
糟了
甘道夫先生
不，朵力
救命
不
索林，不要
(把他的头提来给我)
(杀了他)
不
索林
半身人呢？
没事
比尔博在这里，他很安全
你
你在搞什么？
你差点害死自己
我曾说过你会是个累赘
说你无法存活荒野
说你不配跟我们一起冒险
我这辈子从未如此看走眼过
抱歉我曾质疑你
我也会怀疑我自己
我不是英雄，也不是战士
甚至不是飞贼
这就是那个地方吗？
伊鲁伯
孤山
中土世界最后一个 伟大的矮人王国
我们的家
是渡乌
鸟儿回归孤山了
我亲爱的欧音，那是一只画眉鸟
姑且当成兆头来看吧
-一个好兆头 -说得对
我相信最糟的部分已经过去了
OLD BILBO:
My dear Frodo:
You asked me once...
...if I had told you everything
there was to know about my adventures.
And while I can honestly say
I have told you the truth...
...I may not have told you all of it.
I am old now, Frodo.
I'm not the same Hobbit I once was.
I think it is time for you to know...
...what really happened.
lt began long ago...
...in a land far away to the east...
...the like of which you will not find
in the world today.
There was the city of Dale.
Its markets known far and wide.
Full of the bounties of vine and vale.
Peaceful and prosperous.
For this city lay before the doors
of the greatest kingdom in Middle-earth:
Erebor.
Stronghold of Thror,
King Under the Mountain.
Mightiest of the Dwarf Lords.
Thror ruled with utter surety...
...never doubting his house would endure...
...for his line lay secure
in the lives of his son...
...and grandson.
Ah, Frodo. Erebor.
Built deep within the mountain itself...
...the beauty of this fortress city was legend.
Its wealth lay in the earth...
...in precious gems hewn from rock...
...and in great seams of gold...
...running like rivers through stone.
The skill of the Dwarves was unequaled...
...fashioning objects of great beauty...
...out of diamond, emerald,
ruby and sapphire.
Ever they delved deeper,
down into the dark.
And that is where they found it.
The Heart of the Mountain.
The Arkenstone.
Thror named it "The King's Jewel."
He took it as a sign,
a sign that his right to rule was divine.
All would pay homage to him.
Even the great Elven King, Thranduil.
But the years of peace and plenty
were not to last.
Slowly the days turned sour...
...and the watchful nights closed in.
Thror's love of gold had grown too fierce.
A sickness had begun to grow within him.
lt was a sickness of the mind.
And where sickness thrives...
...bad things will follow.
The first they heard
was a noise like a hurricane...
...coming down from the North.
The pines on the mountain
creaked and cracked in the hot, dry wind.
[GRUNTS]
[WIND WHISTLING]
Balin, sound the alarm.
[BALIN GRUNTS]
Call out the guard. Do it now!
BALIN:
What is it?
Dragon.
Dragon!
He was a firedrake from the North.
[BOTH GRUNT]
Smaug had come.
[PEOPLE SCREAMING]
[HORNS BELLOWING]
[SMAUG ROARS]
[PEOPLE SCREAMING]
Such wanton death was dealt that day.
For this city of Men was nothing to Smaug.
His eye was set on another prize.
For dragons covet gold
with a dark and fierce desire.
[SHOUTS IN DWARVISH]
Aah!
No!
[SMAUG ROARING]
THORIN:
Come on.
Erebor was lost.
For a dragon will guard his plunder...
...as long as he lives.
THORIN:
Run for your lives!
Ah! Help us!
Thranduil would not risk the lives of his kin
against the wrath of the dragon.
No help came from the Elves that day...
...nor any day since.
Robbed of their homeland...
...the Dwarves of Erebor
wandered the wilderness...
...a once mighty people brought low.
The young Dwarf prince took work
where he could find it...
...laboring in the villages of Men.
But always he remembered...
...the mountain smoke beneath the moon...
...the trees like torches blazing bright.
For he had seen dragon fire in the sky...
...and a city turned to ash.
And he never forgave...
...and he never forgot.
[BIRDS CHIRPING]
That, my dear Frodo, is where I come in.
For, quite by chance,
and the will of a Wizard...
...fate decided I would become
part of this tale.
lt began....
Well, it began as you might expect.
ln a hole in the ground...
...there lived a Hobbit.
Not a nasty, dirty, wet hole
full of worms and oozy smells.
This was a Hobbit hole.
And that means good food, a warm hearth...
...and all the comforts of home.
[CHUCKLES]
[OLD BILBO CLEARS THROAT]
Thank you.
What's this?
That is private. Keep your sticky paws off.
It's not ready yet.
Not ready for what?
Reading.
OLD BILBO:
What on earth are these?
FRODO:
Replies to the party invitations.
老天 是今天吗？
They all say they're coming.
Except for the Sackville-Bagginses,
who are demanding you ask them in person.
Are they, indeed? Over my dead body.
They'd probably find that quite agreeable.
They seem to think you have tunnels...
-...overflowing with gold.
-lt was one small chest, hardly overflowing.
And it still smells of Troll.
What on earth are you doing?
[OLD BILBO MUTTERS INDISTINCTLY]
Taking precautions.
You know, I caught her making off
with the silverware once.
-Who?
-Lobelia Sackville-Baggins.
She had all my spoons
stuffed in her pocket. Ha!
Dreadful woman.
Make sure you keep an eye on her
after I'm....
When I'm.... When I'm....
When you're what?
It's nothing. Nothing.
You know, some people are beginning
to wonder about you, Uncle.
-Huh?
-They think you're becoming odd.
Odd? Oh. Hm.
Unsociable.
Unsociable, me? Nonsense.
Be a good lad and put that on the gate.
-Do you think he'll come?
-Who?
Gandalf.
Oh-ho. He wouldn't miss a chance
to let off his Whizpoppers.
He'll give us quite a show, you'll see.
FRODO: Right, then. I'm off.
-Off to where?
FRODO: East-farthing Woods.
I'm going to surprise him.
OLD BILBO:
Well, go on, then. You don't want to be late.
He doesn't approve of being late. Oh, no.
Not that I ever was.
In those days, I was always on time.
I was entirely respectable.
And nothing unexpected...
...ever happened.
[GASPS]
-Good morning.
GANDALF: What do you mean?
Do you wish me a good morning...
...or do you mean that it is a good morning
whether I want it or not?
Or perhaps you mean to say that you feel good
on this particular morning?
Or are you simply stating
that this is a morning to be good on? Hm?
All of them at once, I suppose.
GANDALF:
Hmm.
Can I help you?
That remains to be seen.
I'm looking for someone
to share in an adventure.
An adventure?
No, I don't imagine anyone west of Bree
would have much interest in adventures.
Nasty, disturbing, uncomfortable things.
Make you late for dinner. Heh, heh.
恩，好吧
Mm. Huh.
哼
Hmm.
额，也对
Oh. Ah.
Good morning.
To think that I should have lived
to be "good morninged"...
...by Belladonna Took's son
as if I were selling buttons at the door.
Beg your pardon?
You've changed, and not entirely
for the better, Bilbo Baggins.
I'm sorry, do I know you?
Well, you know my name,
although you don't remember I belong to it.
I'm Gandalf.
And Gandalf means...
...me.
Gandalf?
Not Gandalf the wandering Wizard...
...who made such excellent fireworks?
Old Took used to have them on
Midsummer's Eve. Heh, heh. Ahem.
No idea you were still in business.
And where else should I be?
Where else--? Ahem.
Well, I'm pleased to find you remember
something about me...
...even if it's only my fireworks.
Yes. Well, that's decided.
It'll be very good for you...
...and most amusing for me.
I shall inform the others.
Inform the who? What? No. No. No-- Wait.
We do not want any adventures here,
thank you. Not today. Not--
I suggest you try Over the Hill
or Across the Water.
Good morning.
【甘道夫哼着】
[GANDALF HUMMING]
【吸气声】
[SNIFFS]
【霍比特人喋喋不休】
[HOBBITS CHATTERING IN DISTANCE]
【叹了口气】
[SIGHS]
【门铃声】
[DOORBELL RINGS]
Dwalin, at your service.
Hm. Uh....
Bilbo Baggins, at yours.
Do we know each other?
No.
Which way, laddie? ls it down here?
ls what down where?
Supper.
He said there'd be food and lots of it.
He-- He said? Who said?
DWALIN:
Mmm.
Very good, this. Any more?
What? Oh, yes, yes. Ah.
Help yourself.
Hmm. It's just that, um,
I wasn't expecting company.
[DOORBELL RINGS]
That'll be the door.
Balin, at your service.
-Good evening.
-Yes. Yes, it is.
-Though I think it might rain later.
-Hm?
Am I late?
Late for what?
Oh! Ha, ha!
Evening, brother.
[DWALIN & BALIN CHUCKLE]
By my beard...
...you're shorter and wider than last we met.
BALIN:
Wider, not shorter.
Sharp enough for both of us.
[BOTH LAUGHING]
Uh, excuse me? Sorry, I hate to interrupt.
But the thing is, I'm not entirely sure
you're in the right house.
DWALIN:
Have you eaten?
It's not that I don't like visitors.
I like visitors as much as the next Hobbit.
But I do like to know them
before they come visiting.
-What is this?
-I don't know.
-I think it's cheese. Gone blue.
DWALIN: It's riddled with mold.
The thing is, I don't know either of you.
Not in the slightest.
I don't mean to be blunt,
but I had to speak my mind.
-I'm sorry.
BALIN: You think--?
[CLEARS THROAT]
Apology accepted.
-Ah.
-Now, fill it up, brother, don't stint.
[DOORBELL RINGS]
DWALIN: You wanna get stuck in?
-I could eat again if you insist, brother.
[WHIMPERS]
-Fili.
-And Kili.
[IN UNISON]
At your service.
-You must be Mr. Boggins.
-Nope! You can't come in.
-You've come to the wrong house.
-What?
-Has it been canceled?
-No one told us.
-No, nothing's been canceled.
-That's a relief.
Careful with these.
I just had them sharpened.
-It's nice, this place.
FILI: Yeah.
-Did you do it yourself?
-What? No, it's been in the family for years.
That's my mother's glory box.
Can you please not do that?
Fili, Kili. Come on, give us a hand.
Mr. Dwalin. Ha, ha.
BALIN: Shove this in the hallway.
Otherwise we'll never get everyone in.
BILBO:
"Everyone"? How many more are there?
DWALIN: Where do you want this?
-Oh, no.
DWALIN: It's really heavy.
-No. No. There's nobody home!
Go away and bother somebody else.
There's far too many Dwarves
in my dining room as it is.
If this is some clot-head's idea of a joke...
...I can only say it is in very poor taste.
[GRUNTING]
GLOIN:
Get off, you big lump!
[DWARVES CHATTERING]
Gandalf.
Those are my pri--! Excuse me, not my wine.
Put that back. Put that back.
Not the jam, please.
Excuse me. Excuse me.
It's a tad excessive, isn't it?
Have you got a cheese knife?
-"Cheese knife"? He eats it by the block.
BILBO: Ugh.
No, that's Grandpa Mungo's chair--
No, so is that. Take it back, please.
-I cannot hear what you're saying.
BILBO: It's an antique. Not for sitting on.
That is a book, not a coaster.
And put that map down.
-Excuse me, Mr. Gandalf?
-Yes?
May I tempt you with a cup of chamomile?
Oh, no, thank you, Dori.
A little red wine for me, I think.
NORI: Whoop! Mind out.
-Yes. Ah.
Uh, Fili, Kili. Uh....
Oin, Gloin.
Dwalin, Balin, Bifur, Bofur, Bombur...
-...Dori, Nori. Ori!
-No. Not my prizewinners, thank you.
No, thank you.
[SPEAKS IN DWARVISH]
GANDALF:
Yes, you're quite right, Bifur.
We appear to be one Dwarf short.
He is late, is all. He traveled north
to a meeting of our kin. He will come.
Mr. Gandalf? A little glass of red wine,
as requested.
It's got a fruity bouquet.
GANDALF:
Oh. Cheers.
GLOIN:
Bombur's on his second leg of lamb already.
GANDALF:
Hmm.
[DWARVES CHATTERING]
DWALIN:
No chance. Not from that distance.
BOFUR:
Wanna bet?
Bombur, catch!
[ALL CHEERING]
GANDALF:
I'll help you with that.
[DWARVES CHATTERING]
DWALIN:
Oh, you great galumphing git!
-Who wants an ale? There you go.
KILI: Over here, brother.
DWALIN:
I said have another drink. Here you go.
[ALL LAUGHING]
BOFUR:
Ale on the count of three!
One, two....
Up!
[NORI BELCHES]
[ALL LAUGHING]
[BELCHES]
BOFUR:
I knew you had it in you!
Excuse me, that is a doily, not a dishcloth.
But it's full of holes.
It's supposed to look like that. It's crochet.
And a wonderful game it is too,
if you've got the balls for it.
Bebother and confusticate these Dwarves!
My dear Bilbo, what on earth is the matter?
What's the matter?
I'm surrounded by Dwarves.
What are they doing here?
Oh, they're quite a merry gathering
once you get used to them.
I don't want to get used to them.
Look at the state of my kitchen.
There's mud trod into the carpet.
They've pillaged the pantry.
I won't tell you what they've done
in the bathroom.
They've destroyed the plumbing. I don't
understand what they're doing in my house!
Excuse me. I'm sorry to interrupt,
but what should I do with my plate?
FILI:
Here you go, Ori. Give it to me.
Take that back. Excuse me.
That's my mother's West Farthing pottery.
It's over 1 00 years old!
And can you not do that? You'll blunt them.
BOFUR:
Ooh. Do you hear that, lads?
He says we'll blunt the knives.
[SINGING]
Blunt the knives, bend the forks
Smash the bottles and burn the corks
Chip the glasses and crack the plates
That's what Bilbo Baggins hates
Cut the cloth, tread on the fat
Leave the bones on the bedroom mat
Pour the milk on the pantry floor
Splash the wine on every door
Dump the crocks in a boiling bowl
Pound them up with a thumping pole
When you're finished, if they are whole
Send them down the hall to roll
That's what Bilbo Baggins hates
[ALL LAUGHING]
GANDALF:
Bilbo.
[POUNDING ON DOOR]
He is here.
Gandalf.
I thought you said this place
would be easy to find.
I lost my way, twice.
I wouldn't have found it at all
had it not been for that mark on the door.
Mark? There's no mark on that door.
lt was painted a week ago.
There is a mark. I put it there myself.
Bilbo Baggins, allow me to introduce
the leader of our company:
Thorin Oakenshield.
So...
...this is the Hobbit.
Tell me, Mr. Baggins,
have you done much fighting?
-Pardon me?
THORIN: Ax or sword?
What's your weapon of choice?
Well, I do have some skill at conkers,
if you must know...
...but I fail to see why that's relevant.
Thought as much.
He looks more like a grocer than a burglar.
[ALL CHUCKLING]
What news from the meeting in Ered Luin?
Did they all come?
-Aye. Envoys from all seven kingdoms.
BALIN: All of them!
DWALIN: And what did the Dwarves
of the lron Hills say?
ls Dain with us?
They will not come.
[ALL MURMURING]
THORIN:
They say this quest is ours and ours alone.
BILBO:
You're going on a quest?
Bilbo, my dear fellow,
let us have a little more light.
Far to the east...
...over ranges and rivers...
...beyond woodlands and wastelands...
...lies a single, solitary peak.
"The Lonely Mountain."
Aye, Oin has read the portents...
...and the portents say it is time.
Ravens have been seen flying back
to the mountain, as it was foretold.
"When the birds of yore return to Erebor...
...the reign of the beast will end."
Uh, what beast?
That would be a reference
to Smaug the Terrible...
...chiefest and greatest calamity of our age.
Airborne fire-breather.
Teeth like razors, claws like meat hooks.
-Extremely fond of precious metals.
-Yes, I know what a dragon is.
I'm not afraid. I'm up for it.
I'll give him a taste of Dwarfish iron
right up his jacksie!
NORI: Good lad, Ori!
-Sit down.
The task would be difficult enough
with an army behind us...
...but we number just 1 3.
And not 1 3 of the best...
...nor brightest.
NORI:
Here, who are you calling dim?
OIN:
Sorry, what did he say?
FILI:
We may be few in number...
...but we're fighters, all of us,
to the last Dwarf.
And you forget,
we have a Wizard in our company.
Gandalf will have killed
hundreds of dragons in his time.
Oh, well, no. I wouldn't say--
DORI: How many, then?
-What?
Well, how many dragons have you killed?
[COUGHS]
Go on. Give us a number.
[ALL SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY]
Excuse me. Please.
[SHOUTS IN DWARVISH]
If we have read these signs...
...do you not think others
will have read them too?
Rumors have begun to spread.
The dragon, Smaug,
has not been seen for 60 years.
Eyes look east to the mountain, assessing...
...wondering, weighing the risk.
Perhaps the vast wealth of our people
now lies unprotected.
Do we sit back while others claim
what is rightfully ours?
Or do we seize this chance
to take back Erebor?
[ALL CHEERING]
BALIN:
You forget, the Front Gate is sealed.
There is no way into the mountain.
That, my dear Balin, is not entirely true.
How came you by this?
lt was given to me by your father.
By Thrain. For safekeeping.
lt is yours now.
FILI:
If there is a key...
...there must be a door.
These runes speak of a hidden
passage to the Lower Halls.
There's another way in.
Well, if we can find it,
but Dwarf doors are invisible when closed.
[GANDALF SIGHS]
The answer lies hidden somewhere
in this map...
...and I do not have the skill to find it.
But there are others in Middle-earth
who can.
The task I have in mind
will require a great deal of stealth...
...and no small amount of courage.
But if we are careful and clever,
I believe that it can be done.
That's why we need a burglar.
Hmm. And a good one too.
An expert, I'd imagine.
GLOIN:
And are you?
Am I what?
He said he's an expert. Hey.
Me? No. No, no, no. I'm not a burglar.
I've never stolen a thing in my life.
Well, I'm afraid I have to agree
with Mr. Baggins.
He's hardly burglar material.
Nope.
Aye, the Wild is no place for gentle folk
who can neither fight nor fend for themselves.
KILI:
He's just fine.
[CHATTERING]
Enough!
If I say Bilbo Baggins is a burglar,
then a burglar he is.
Hobbits are remarkably light on their feet.
ln fact, they can pass unseen by most,
if they choose.
And, while the dragon is accustomed
to the smell of Dwarf...
...the scent of a Hobbit
is all but unknown to him...
...which gives us a distinct advantage.
You asked me to find the 14th member of
this company and I have chosen Mr. Baggins.
There's a lot more to him
than appearances suggest.
And he's got a great deal more to offer
than any of you know.
Including himself.
You must trust me on this.
Very well.
-We will do it your way.
-No, no.
THORIN: Give him the contract.
-We're in. We're off.
BALIN:
It's just the usual.
Summary of out-of-pocket expenses...
...time required, remuneration...
...funeral arrangements, so forth.
Funeral arrangements?
[BILBO SIGHS]
I cannot guarantee his safety.
Understood.
Nor will I be responsible for his fate.
Agreed.
"Terms: Cash on delivery, up to but not
exceeding one-fourteenth of total profit, if any."
Hmm. Seems fair.
"Present company shall not be liable
for injuries inflicted by...
...or sustained as a consequence thereof,
including, but not limited to lacerations...
...evisceration...."
Incineration?
Aye. He'll melt the flesh off your bones
in the blink of an eye.
[WHIMPERS]
-You all right, laddie?
-Huh? Yeah.
Feel a bit faint.
-Think furnace with wings.
BILBO: Air.
I need air.
Flash of light, searing pain, then poof.
You're nothing more than a pile of ash.
BILBO:
Hmm.
Nope.
GANDALF:
Oh, very helpful, Bofur.
I'll be all right.
Just let me sit quietly for a moment.
You've been sitting quietly for far too long.
Tell me, when did doilies
and your mother's dishes...
...become so important to you?
I remember a young Hobbit who was always
running off in search of Elves in the woods.
Who would stay out late,
come home after dark...
...trailing mud and twigs and fireflies.
A young Hobbit who would have liked
nothing better...
...than to find out what was beyond
the borders of the Shire.
The world is not in your books and maps.
It's out there.
I can't just go running off into the blue.
I am a Baggins of Bag-end.
You are also a Took.
Did you know that your
great-great-great-great-uncle Bullroarer Took...
...was so large, he could ride a real horse?
-Yes.
-Yes, well, he could.
ln the Battle of Green Fields,
he charged the Goblin ranks.
He swung his club so hard,
it knocked the Goblin king's head clean off...
...and it sailed 1 00 yards through the air
and went down a rabbit hole.
And thus, the battle was won.
And the game of golf invented
at the same time.
I do believe you made that up.
Well, all good stories
deserve embellishment.
You'll have a tale or two to tell of your own
when you come back.
Can you promise that I will come back?
No.
And if you do...
...you will not be the same.
That's what I thought.
Sorry, Gandalf, I can't sign this.
You've got the wrong Hobbit.
lt appears we have lost our burglar.
Probably for the best.
The odds were always against us.
After all, what are we?
Merchants, miners...
...tinkers, toy-makers.
Heh, heh. Hardly the stuff of legend.
There are a few warriors amongst us.
Old warriors.
I would take each and every one
of these Dwarves...
...over an army from the lron Hills.
For when I called upon them,
they answered.
Loyalty, honor...
...a willing heart.
I can ask no more than that.
You don't have to do this.
You have a choice.
You've done honorably by our people.
You have built a new life for us
in the Blue Mountains.
A life of peace and plenty.
A life that is worth more than
all the gold in Erebor.
From my grandfather to my father,
this has come to me.
They dreamt of the day when the Dwarves
of Erebor would reclaim their homeland.
There is no choice, Balin.
Not for me.
Then we are with you, laddie.
We will see it done.
[DWARVES HUMMING]
[SINGING]
Far over the misty mountains cold
To dungeons deep
And caverns old
We must away
'Ere break of day
To find our long-forgotten gold
The pines were roaring on the height
The winds were moaning in the night
The fire was red, it flaming spread
The trees like torches blazed with light
[MOANS]
Hello?
Yes.
[CHICKENS CLUCKING]
Here, Mr. Bilbo, where are you off to?
-Can't stop, I'm already late!
-Late for what?
I'm going on an adventure!
DORI: I said it. Didn't I say it?
Coming here was a waste of time.
GLOIN:
That's true enough.
DORI: Ridiculous notion. Use a Hobbit?
A Halfling?
Whose idea was it anyway?
BILBO:
Wait!
THORIN:
Whoa, whoa.
[PONIES NEIGHING]
I signed it.
Here.
[PONY SNORTS]
BALIN:
Everything appears to be in order.
Welcome, Master Baggins...
...to the company of Thorin Oakenshield.
[ALL CHUCKLING AND CHATTERING]
Give him a pony.
No, no, that won't be necessary.
Thank you. I'm sure I can keep up on foot.
I've done my fair share of walking holidays,
you know?
Even got as far as Frogmorton once. Aah!
[NEIGHS]
OIN:
Come on, Nori. Pay up.
KILI: One more.
OIN: Thanks, lad.
What's that about?
Oh, they took wagers
on whether or not you'd turn up.
Most of them bet that you wouldn't.
And what did you think?
Well....
My dear fellow,
I never doubted you for a second.
[SNEEZES THEN SIGHS]
It's horse hair. Having a reaction.
[GROANS]
No, wait, wait, stop.
Stop! We have to turn around.
GANDALF:
What on earth is the matter?
-I forgot my handkerchief.
BOFUR: Here.
Use this.
[ALL CHUCKLING]
THORIN:
Move on.
GANDALF: You'll have to manage
without pocket handkerchiefs...
...and a good many other things,
Bilbo Baggins...
...before we reach our journey's end.
You were born to the rolling hills
and little rivers of the Shire.
But home is now behind you.
The world is ahead.
[SNORING]
Hello, girl. Who's a good girl?
It's our little secret, Myrtle.
You must tell no one. Shh, shh.
[SCREECHING IN DISTANCE]
What was that?
Orcs.
Orcs?
Throat-cutters.
There'll be dozens of them out there.
The lone-lands are crawling with them.
They strike in the wee small hours
when everyone's asleep.
Quick and quiet, no screams.
Just lots of blood.
[BOTH CHUCKLING]
THORIN:
You think that's funny?
You think a night raid by Orcs is a joke?
We didn't mean anything by it.
THORIN:
No, you didn't.
You know nothing of the world.
BALIN:
Don't mind him, laddie.
Thorin has more cause than most
to hate Orcs.
After the dragon took the Lonely Mountain...
...King Thror tried to reclaim
the ancient Dwarf kingdom of Moria.
But our enemy had got there first.
Moria had been taken by legions of Orcs...
...led by the most vile of all their race:
Azog the Defiler.
The giant Gundabad Orc...
...had sworn to wipe out the line of Durin.
He began...
...by beheading the king.
[ROARING]
No!
BALIN: Thrain, Thorin's father,
was driven mad by grief.
He went missing. Taken prisoner or killed...
...we did not know.
We were leaderless.
Defeat and death...
...were upon us.
That is when I saw him.
A young Dwarf prince...
...facing down the pale Orc.
He stood alone against this terrible foe.
[AZOG ROARS]
His armor rent...
...wielding nothing but an oaken branch
as a shield.
[THORIN YELLS]
[AZOG SCREAMING]
Azog the Defiler learned that day...
...that the line of Durin
would not be so easily broken.
[THORIN SHOUTING IN DWARVISH]
[ALL YELLING]
Our forces rallied...
...and drove the Orcs back.
And our enemy...
...had been defeated.
But there was no feast...
...nor song that night...
...for our dead
were beyond the count of grief.
We few had survived.
And I thought to myself then...
...there is one who I could follow.
There is one...
...I could call king.
And the pale Orc?
What happened to him?
He slunk back into the hole
whence he came.
That filth died of his wounds long ago.
[GROWLING]
[IN BLACK SPEECH]
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
Here, Mr. Gandalf, can't you do something
about this deluge?
lt is raining, Master Dwarf...
...and it will continue to rain
until the rain is done.
If you wish to change the weather of the world,
you should find yourself another Wizard.
-Are there any?
GANDALF: What?
BILBO: Other Wizards.
GANDALF: There are five of us.
The greatest of our order
is Saruman the White.
Then there are the two Blue Wizards....
Do you know,
I've quite forgotten their names.
And who is the fifth?
Well, that would be Radagast the Brown.
ls he a great Wizard? Or is he more like you?
I think he's a very great Wizard,
in his own way.
He's a gentle soul who prefers
the company of animals to others.
He keeps a watchful eye
over the vast forest lands...
...to the east. And a good thing too.
For always evil will look to find
a foothold in this world.
Not good. Not good at all.
[SNIFFING]
Eww.
[WHISTLING]
Oh, no. Sebastian.
[SEBASTIAN WHIMPERING]
Good gracious.
[SEBASTIAN WHIMPERS
THEN RADAGAST SHUSHES]
Come on.
Move back! Give him some air,
for goodness sake.
There. There.
I don't understand why it's not working.
It's not as if it's witchcraft.
Witchcraft.
Oh, but it is.
A dark and powerful magic.
[CHITTERING]
[WHIMPERS]
[ANIMALS SQUEAKING]
[RADAGAST CHANTING
IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
[SEBASTIAN GRUNTING]
Where on this good earth
did those foul creatures come from?
[BIRD CHIRPING]
The old fortress?
Show me.
THORIN:
We'll camp here for the night.
Fili, Kili, look after the ponies.
Make sure you stay with them.
A farmer and his family used to live here.
THORIN: Oin, Gloin. Get a fire going.
OIN: Aye.
Right you are.
I think it would be wiser to move on.
We could make for the Hidden Valley.
I have told you already...
...I will not go near that place.
Why not? The Elves could help us.
We could get food, rest, advice.
THORIN:
I do not need their advice.
We have a map that we cannot read.
Lord Elrond could help us.
Help?
A dragon attacks Erebor.
What help came from the Elves?
Orcs plunder Moria...
...desecrate our sacred halls.
The Elves looked on and did nothing.
And you ask me to seek out the very people
who betrayed my grandfather.
Who betrayed my father.
You are neither of them.
I did not give you that map and key
for you to hold onto the past.
I did not know that they were yours to keep.
Everything all right?
Gandalf, where are you going?
GANDALF: To seek the company of the
only one around here who's got any sense.
-And who's that?
GANDALF: Myself, Mr. Baggins.
I've had enough of Dwarves for one day.
Come on, Bombur, we're hungry.
ls he coming back?
[DWARVES CHATTERING]
He's been a long time.
-Who?
-Gandalf.
He's a Wizard. He does as he chooses.
Here, do us a favor. Take this to the lads.
Stop it. You've had plenty.
GLOIN: Aye, it's not a bad stew, Bombur.
I've had worse.
NORI:
Dori could've cooked it. Ha-ha-ha.
DORI:
Hilarious.
What's the matter?
-We're supposed to be looking after the ponies.
-Only we've encountered a slight problem.
KILI:
We had 1 6.
FILI:
Now there's 14.
KILI:
Daisy and Bungo are missing.
Well, that's not good. Ha, ha.
And that is not good at all.
Shouldn't we tell Thorin?
Uh, no. Let's not worry him.
As our official burglar,
we thought you might like to look into it.
Well, uh....
-Look, something big uprooted these trees.
-That was our thinking.
It's something very big
and possibly quite dangerous.
Hey.
There's a light.
Over here.
Stay down.
[GRUNTING AND LAUGHTER]
What is it?
Trolls.
Oh.
[PONIES NEIGHING]
He's got Myrtle and Minty.
I think they're gonna eat them.
We have to do something.
Yes, you should.
Mountain Trolls are slow and stupid,
and you're so small, they'll never see you.
It's perfectly safe. We'll be behind you.
If you run into trouble, hoot twice
like a barn owl and once like a brown owl.
BILBO: Twice like a barn owl.
No, twice like a brown-- Once like a--
Like a-- Are you sure this is a good idea?
BERT:
Mutton yesterday, mutton today...
...and, blimey, if it don't look like
mutton again tomorrow.
WILLIAM:
Quit your griping.
These ain't sheep. These is fresh nags.
Oh! I don't like horse. I never have.
Not enough fat on them.
Well, it's better than leathery old farmer.
All skin and bone, he was.
I'm still picking bits of him out of me teeth.
[TOM SNEEZES]
Well, that's lovely, that is. A floater.
WILLIAM:
Might improve the flavor.
Ah. There's more where that came from.
-Oh, no, you don't!
TOM: Ow!
[TOM WHIMPERING]
Sit down!
[SNEEZES]
[TOM BLOWING NOSE]
Well, I hope you're gonna gut these nags.
I don't like the stinky parts.
-Ow!
-I said sit down.
I'm starving!
Now, are we having horse tonight or what?
BERT: Shut your cakehole.
You'll eat what I give you.
WILLIAM: How come he's the cook?
Everything tastes the same.
Everything tastes like chicken.
TOM:
Except the chicken.
WILLIAM:
What tastes like fish!
I'm just saying,
a little appreciation would be nice.
[PONY NEIGHS]
Oh. "Thank you very much, Bert.
Lovely stew, Bert."
-How hard is that?
-Shh. Shh, shh. Shh.
BERT:
Just needs a sprinkle of squirrel dung.
Here, that's my grog.
[TOM WHIMPERS]
Sorry. Ow!
Ooh. That is beautifully balanced, that is.
Wrap your laughing gear around that, eh?
Good, isn't it?
[BERT CHUCKLES]
That's why I'm the cook.
[WILLIAM GRUNTS]
WILLIAM: Oh, me guts are grumbling.
I got to snaffle something.
-Flesh, I need flesh.
TOP: Ah! Ah!
[TOM BLOWS NOSE]
[SCREAMS]
Blimey!
Bert. Bert!
Look what's come out of me hooter.
It's got arms and legs and everything.
BERT:
What is it?
I don't know.
But I don't like the way it wriggles around.
What are you, then? An oversized squirrel?
I'm a burglar-- Uh, Hobbit.
A burglar Hobbit?
Can we cook him?
We can try.
He wouldn't make more than a mouthful.
Not when he's skinned and boned.
Perhaps there's more burglar Hobbits
around these parts.
Might be enough for a pie.
-Grab him!
TOM: He's too quick.
WILLIAM:
Right. Come here, you little--
Gotcha.
Are there any more of you little fellas
hiding where you shouldn't?
No.
He's lying.
-No, I'm not!
-Hold his toes over the fire.
Make him squeal!
[SQUEALS]
Drop him!
You what?
I said...
...drop him.
[GROWLS]
[BILBO YELLS]
[ALL YELLING]
[TOM SQUEALS]
[ROARS]
WILLIAM:
Get the sacks! Stick them in the sacks!
[PONIES NEIGHING]
[TOM SCREAMING]
Ow!
[SCREAMS]
KILI:
Come on! Get up!
-Bilbo!
-Don't!
Lay down your arms...
...or we'll rip his off.
[SWORD CLANGS]
NORI:
Oh! That's hot, that's hot, that's hot!
Don't bother cooking them.
Let's just sit on them
and squash them into jelly.
They should be sautéed and grilled
with a sprinkle of sage.
BALIN:
ls this really necessary?
That does sound quite nice.
BOMBUR: Untie me, mister.
GLOIN: Eat someone your own size.
WILLIAM:
Never mind the seasoning.
We ain't got all night.
Dawn ain't far away.
Let's get a move on.
I don't fancy being turned to stone.
BILBO:
Wait!
You are making a terrible mistake.
You can't reason with them. They're half-wits!
Half-wits? What does that make us?
I meant with the seasoning.
What about the seasoning?
Well, have you smelt them?
You're gonna need something stronger
than sage before you plate this lot up.
BOMBUR: Traitor!
-What do you know about cooking Dwarf?
BERT:
Shut up.
Let the flurgaburburhobbit talk.
The secret to cooking Dwarf is....
BERT: Yes? Come on. Tell us the secret.
-It's, uh....
Yes, I'm telling you. The secret is...
...to skin them first.
NORI:
What? Skin us?
Tom, get me filleting knife.
I'll skin you, you little--!
DWALIN:
I won't forget that. I won't forget it.
What a load of rubbish.
I've eaten plenty with their skins on.
Scarf them, I say, boots and all.
TOM:
He's right.
Nothing wrong with a bit of raw Dwarf.
Nice and crunchy.
Oh, not that one. He's infected.
-Huh?
-You what?
Yeah, he's got worms in his tubes.
TOM: Eww!
BOMBUR: Aah!
ln fact, they all have.
They're infested with parasites.
It's a terrible business.
I wouldn't risk it. I really wouldn't.
Parasites? Did he say "parasites"?
We don't have parasites. You have parasites!
OIN:
What are you talking about, laddie?
[KILI GRUNTS]
I've got parasites as big as my arm.
Mine are the biggest parasites.
I've got huge parasites.
[DWARVES CHATTERING]
KILI: We're riddled.
ORI: Yes, I'm riddled.
Yes, we are, badly.
What would you have us do, then?
Let them all go?
-Well....
-You think I don't know what you're up to?
This little ferret is taking us for fools.
-Ferret?
-Fools?
GANDALF:
The dawn will take you all.
-Who's that?
-No idea.
Can we eat him too?
[TROLLS GROANING]
[ALL LAUGHING]
Get your foot out of my back.
[GRUNTING]
[DWARVES CHATTERING]
Ah.
Where did you go to, if I may ask?
To look ahead.
-What brought you back?
-Looking behind.
Nasty business.
Still, they're all in one piece.
No thanks to your burglar.
He had the nous to play for time.
None of the rest of you thought of that.
They must have come down
from the Ettenmoors.
THORIN: Since when do Mountain Trolls
venture this far south?
Ooh. Not for an age.
Not since a darker power ruled these lands.
They could not have moved in daylight.
There must be a cave nearby.
[INSECTS BUZZING]
NORI:
Oh, what's that stench?
GANDALF:
It's a Troll-hoard.
Be careful what you touch.
[DWARVES COUGHING]
Seems a shame
just to leave it lying around.
-Anyone could take it.
-Agreed.
-Nori.
NORI: Yeah?
Get a shovel.
These swords were not made by any Troll.
Nor were they made
by any smith among Men.
These were forged in Gondolin...
...by the High Elves of the First Age.
You could not wish for a finer blade.
BOFUR: Set it down.
GLOIN: That's good.
BOFUR:
All right, come on. Quick.
We're making a long-term deposit.
THORIN:
Let's get out of this foul place.
Come on, let's go.
Bofur, Gloin, Nori.
GANDALF: Bilbo.
BILBO: Hmm?
Here.
This is about your size.
I can't take this.
The blade is of Elvish make...
...which means it will glow blue
when Orcs or Goblins are nearby.
I have never used a sword in my life.
And I hope you never have to.
But if you do, remember this:
True courage is about knowing
not when to take a life...
...but when to spare one.
THORIN:
Something's coming!
-Gandalf.
GANDALF: Stay together!
Hurry now! Arm yourselves!
Thieves! Fire! Murder!
GANDALF:
Radagast.
It's Radagast the Brown.
Well....
What on earth are you doing here?
I was looking for you, Gandalf.
Something's wrong.
Something's terribly wrong.
Yes?
Oh.
Just give me a minute.
Oh. I had a thought and now I've lost it.
lt was right there on the tip of my tongue.
Oh. It's not a thought at all.
It's a silly old...
...stick insect.
The Greenwood is sick, Gandalf.
A darkness has fallen over it.
Nothing grows anymore.
At least, nothing good.
The air is foul with decay.
But worse are the webs.
GANDALF:
Webs? What do you mean?
Spiders, Gandalf.
Giant ones.
Some kind of spawn of Ungoliant,
or I am not a Wizard.
I followed their trail.
They came from Dol Guldur.
GANDALF:
Huh?
Dol Guldur?
But the old fortress is abandoned.
No, Gandalf.
'Tis not.
RADAGAST:
A dark power dwells in there...
...such as I have never felt before.
lt is the shadow of an ancient horror.
One that can summon the spirits...
...of the dead.
I saw him, Gandalf.
From out of the darkness...
...a Necromancer has come.
NECROMANCER:
Radagast.
[BIRDS SCREECHING]
RADAGAST:
Quick! Quick, quick! Quick, quick!
Wait for me!
[GASPS]
Sorry.
Try a little Old Toby.
It'll help settle your nerves.
And out.
[RADAGAST SIGHS]
Now, a Necromancer. Are you sure?
That is not...
...from the world of the living.
[RADAGAST GASPS]
Was that a wolf?
Are there wolves out there?
Wolves? No, that is not a wolf.
[GROWLING]
[ALL YELLING]
THORIN:
Kili! Get your bow!
Warg scouts.
-Which means an Orc pack is not far behind.
-Orc pack?
Who did you tell about your quest
beyond your kin?
-No one.
-Who did you tell?
No one, I swear.
What in Durin's name is going on?
You are being hunted.
-We have to get out of here.
-We can't. We have no ponies.
[WARG HOWLS IN DISTANCE]
ORI:
They bolted.
I'll draw them off.
These are Gundabad Wargs.
They will outrun you.
These are Rhosgobel rabbits.
I'd like to see them try.
[WARGS HOWLING]
[ORC SPEAKS IN BLACK SPEECH]
RADAGAST:
Come on! Come on!
Come and get me! Ha, ha!
[SPEAKS IN BLACK SPEECH]
[RADAGAST LAUGHING]
[WARGS GROWLING]
Come on.
Stay together.
Move!
THORIN:
Ori, no! Get back.
All of you, come on. Quick!
Where are you leading us?
[SNIFFING]
[GROWLING]
[WARG SCREECHES IN DISTANCE]
[GROWLS]
[ORC ROARS]
[ORC GROWLING IN DISTANCE]
[WEAPONS CLANGING IN DISTANCE]
[IN BLACK SPEECH]
[WARGS HOWLING]
GANDALF:
Move!
Run!
[WARGS HOWLING AND BARKING]
There they are!
This way! Quickly!
[GROWLING]
There's more coming!
THORIN:
Kili! Shoot them!
We're surrounded!
DORI:
Where's Gandalf?
DWALIN:
He's abandoned us.
[LAUGHS]
Hold your ground!
This way, you fools!
THORIN:
Come on, move!
Quickly! All of you!
BOFUR:
Come on!
THORIN:
Go, go, go!
Eight, nine, 1 0.
Kili! Run!
[WARGS GROWLING]
[HORN SOUNDS]
[YELLS]
[GROWLING]
Elves.
DWALIN: I cannot see where the pathway leads.
Do we follow it or no?
Follow it, of course.
I think that would be wise.
GLOIN:
Come on now, brother.
[GRUNTS]
The Valley of Imladris.
ln the common tongue,
it's known by another name.
Rivendell.
GANDALF: Here lies the Last Homely House
East of the Sea.
This was your plan all along.
To seek refuge with our enemy.
You have no enemies here,
Thorin Oakenshield.
The only ill will to be found in this valley
is that which you bring yourself.
You think the Elves will give our quest
their blessing?
They will try to stop us.
Of course they will. But we have questions
that need to be answered.
If we are to be successful,
this will need to be handled with tact.
And respect.
And no small degree of charm.
Which is why you will leave the talking
to me.
LINDIR:
Mithrandir.
Ah. Lindir.
Stay sharp.
[IN ELVISH]
I must speak with Lord Elrond.
[IN ENGLISH]
My Lord Elrond is not here.
Not here?
Where is he?
[HORN SOUNDS]
[THORIN SHOUTS IN DWARVISH]
THORIN:
Close ranks!
-Gandalf.
-Lord Elrond.
[IN ELVISH]
[IN ENGLISH] Strange for Orcs to come
so close to our borders.
Something or someone
has drawn them near.
[IN ENGLISH]
That may have been us.
Welcome, Thorin, son of Thrain.
I do not believe we have met.
You have your grandfather's bearing.
I knew Thror
when he ruled Under the Mountain.
Indeed? He made no mention of you.
[SPEAKING IN ELVISH]
GLOIN:
What is he saying?
Does he offer us insult?
No, Master Gloin, he's offering you food.
[ALL MURMURING]
Well, in that case, lead on.
BOFUR:
Hey. Come on.
Try it. Just a mouthful.
I don't like green food.
Where's the meat?
[GROWLS]
Have they got any chips?
Kind of you to invite us.
Not really dressed for dinner.
Well, you never are.
[GANDALF CHUCKLES]
[DWARVES CHUCKLING]
[CHUCKLES]
This is Orcrist, the Goblin-cleaver.
A famous blade...
...forged by the High Elves of the West,
my kin.
May it serve you well.
And this is Glamdring...
...the Foehammer.
Sword of the King of Gondolin.
These were made for the Goblin Wars
of the First Age.
I wouldn't bother, laddie. Swords are
named for the great deeds they do in war.
What are you saying,
my sword hasn't seen battle?
I'm not actually sure it is a sword.
More of a letter opener, really.
How did you come by these?
We found them in a Troll-hoard
on the Great East Road...
...shortly before we were
ambushed by Orcs.
And what were you doing
on the Great East Road?
THORIN:
Our business is no concern of Elves.
GANDALF: For goodness sake, Thorin,
show him the map.
lt is the legacy of my people.
lt is mine to protect, as are its secrets.
Save me from the stubbornness
of Dwarves.
Your pride will be your downfall.
You stand in the presence
of one of the few in Middle-earth...
...who can read that map.
Show it to Lord Elrond.
Thorin, no.
Erebor.
What is your interest in this map?
It's mainly academic.
As you know, this sort of artifact
sometimes contains hidden text.
You still read ancient Dwarvish,
do you not?
[ELROND SPEAKS IN ELVISH]
Moon runes?
Of course.
An easy thing to miss.
ELROND:
Well, in this case, that is true.
Moon runes can only be read
by the light of a moon...
...of the same shape and season
as the day on which they were written.
Can you read them?
ELROND: These runes were written
on a Midsummer's Eve...
...by the light of a crescent moon
nearly 200 years ago.
lt would seem you were meant
to come to Rivendell.
Fate is with you, Thorin Oakenshield.
The same moon shines upon us tonight.
"Stand by the gray stone
when the thrush knocks...
...and the setting sun with the last light
of Durin's Day...
-...will shine upon the keyhole."
-Durin's Day?
lt is the start of the Dwarves' new year,
when the last moon of autumn...
...and the first sun of winter
appear in the sky together.
This is ill news.
Summer is passing.
Durin's Day will soon be upon us.
We still have time.
-Time? For what?
-To find the entrance.
We have to be standing in exactly
the right spot at exactly the right time.
Then, and only then,
can the door be opened.
So this is your purpose,
to enter the mountain?
What of it?
There are some
who would not deem it wise.
What do you mean?
You are not the only guardian
to stand watch over Middle-earth.
[WARGS HOWLING]
[WARGS GROWLING]
[IN BLACK SPEECH]
AZOG [IN BLACK SPEECH]:
[AZOG SHOUTS IN BLACK SPEECH]
[GROWLING]
[AZOG ROARS]
[CHATTERING]
No, you did the same thing.
-It's not like you didn't do it.
DWALIN: Dori! Here, take that.
Bombur!
[ALL LAUGHING]
With or without our help, these Dwarves
will march on the mountain.
They're determined to reclaim
their homeland.
I do not believe Thorin Oakenshield
feels that he is answerable to anyone.
Nor, for that matter, am I.
lt is not me you must answer to.
Lady Galadriel.
Mithrandir.
[IN ELVISH]
[IN ENGLISH]
I had no idea Lord Elrond had sent for you.
MAN:
He didn't.
I did.
Ah.
Saruman.
You've been busy of late, my friend.
Tell me, Gandalf...
...did you think these plans and schemes
of yours would go unnoticed?
GANDALF:
Unnoticed?
No.
I'm simply doing what I feel to be right.
[IN ENGLISH]
The dragon has long been on your mind.
That is true, my lady.
Smaug owes allegiance to no one.
But if he should side with the enemy...
...a dragon could be used
to terrible effect.
What enemy?
Gandalf, the enemy is defeated.
Sauron is vanquished.
He can never regain his full strength.
Gandalf, for 400 years
we have lived in peace...
...a hard-won, watchful peace.
Are we? Are we at peace?
Trolls have come down
from the mountains.
They are raiding villages,
destroying farms.
Orcs have attacked us on the road.
Hardly a prelude to war.
Always you must meddle...
...looking for trouble where none exists.
Let him speak.
There is something at work
beyond the evil of Smaug.
Something far more powerful.
We can remain blind to it, but it will not
be ignoring us, that I can promise you.
A sickness lies over the Greenwood.
The woodsmen who live there now
call it Mirkwood.
And they say....
Well? Don't stop now.
Tell us what the woodsmen say.
They speak of a Necromancer
living in Dol Guldur.
A sorcerer who can summon the dead.
That's absurd.
No such power exists in this world.
This Necromancer is nothing more
than a mortal man.
A conjurer dabbling in black magic.
And so I thought too.
-But Radagast has seen--
SARUMAN: Radagast?
Do not speak to me
of Radagast the Brown.
He's a foolish fellow.
Well, he's odd, I grant you.
He lives a solitary life.
It's not that. It's his excessive
consumption of mushrooms.
They've addled his brain
and yellowed his teeth.
I've warned him.
lt is unbefitting one of the lstari
to be wandering the woods....
GALADRIEL:
You carry something.
lt came to you from Radagast.
He found it in Dol Guldur.
GANDALF:
Yes.
GALADRIEL:
Show me.
SARUMAN:
--listen to me.
I would think I was talking to myself
for all the attention that he paid.
By all means....
What is that?
A relic of Mordor.
A Morgul Blade.
Made for the Witchking of Angmar.
And buried with him.
When Angmar fell...
...the Men of the North took his body
and all that he possessed...
...and sealed it within
the High Fells of Rhudaur.
Deep within the rock they buried him...
...in a tomb so dark...
...it would never come to light.
This is not possible.
A powerful spell lies upon those tombs.
They cannot be opened.
What proof do we have this weapon
came from Angmar's grave?
-I have none.
-Because there is none.
Let us examine what we know.
A single Orc pack...
...has dared to cross the Bruinen.
A dagger from a bygone age
has been found.
And a human sorcerer who calls himself
"The Necromancer"...
...has taken up residence
in a ruined fortress.
It's not so very much after all.
The question of this Dwarvish company,
however, troubles me deeply.
I'm not convinced, Gandalf.
I do not feel I can condone such a quest.
If they'd come to me, I might have
spared them this disappointment.
I do not pretend to understand your reason
for raising their hopes.
GALADRIEL:
They are leaving.
GANDALF:
Yes.
GALADRIEL:
You knew.
[SARUMAN SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY]
No, I'm afraid there is nothing else for it.
My Lord Elrond.
The Dwarves, they're gone.
THORIN:
Be on your guard.
We're about to step over
the Edge of the Wild.
Balin, you know these paths. Lead on.
BALIN:
Aye.
THORIN:
Master Baggins...
...I suggest you keep up.
GALADRIEL: You will follow them.
GANDALF: Yes.
GALADRIEL: You are right to help
Thorin Oakenshield.
But I fear this quest has set in motion...
...forces we do not yet understand.
The riddle of the Morgul Blade
must be answered.
Something moves in the shadows unseen,
hidden from our sight.
lt will not show itself.
Not yet.
But every day it grows in strength.
You must be careful.
Mithrandir?
Why the Halfling?
I do not know.
Saruman believes
that it is only great power...
...that can hold evil in check.
But that is not what I have found.
I have found it is the small things...
...everyday deeds of ordinary folk...
...that keeps the darkness at bay.
Simple acts of kindness and love.
Why Bilbo Baggins?
Perhaps it is because I'm afraid...
...and he gives me courage.
Do not be afraid, Mithrandir.
You are not alone.
[IN ELVISH]
[THUNDER RUMBLING]
THORIN:
Hey! Hold on!
BILBO: Aah!
DWALIN: Bilbo!
[BILBO YELLS]
We must find shelter!
Look out!
[ALL SCREAMING]
GLOIN:
Look out, brother!
KILI:
Hold on!
This is no thunderstorm.
It's a thunder-battle!
Look!
Well, bless me.
The legends are true.
Giants! Stone-Giants!
Take cover, you fool!
Hold on!
KILI: What's happening?
FILI: Grab my hand!
[ALL SCREAMING]
THORIN: Go, go, go!
BALIN: Run! Get off! Get off!
-Run!
DORI: Look out!
Look out!
THORIN:
Jump!
Come on!
Hold on!
No!
No! Kili!
[ALL PANTING]
GLOIN:
It's all right! They're alive!
Where's Bilbo? Where's the Hobbit?
[BILBO GRUNTING]
There!
THORIN:
Get him!
Aah!
-Grab my hand!
-Bilbo!
DORI: Ori, be careful!
ORI: Take it!
DWALIN: I've got you, lad.
ORI: Grab on! Grab on!
[GRUNTING]
Come on. Get him.
GLOIN:
Come on, lad. Up you get.
I thought we'd lost our burglar.
He's been lost ever since he left home.
He should never have come.
He has no place amongst us.
Dwalin!
DWALIN: lt looks safe enough.
THORIN: Search to the back.
Caves in the mountain
are seldom unoccupied.
DWALIN:
There's nothing here.
Right, then. Let's get a fire started.
No. No fires. Not in this place.
Get some sleep.
We start at first light.
We were to wait in the mountains
until Gandalf joined us.
-That was the plan.
-Plans change.
Bofur, take the first watch.
[THUNDER CRASHING]
[SNIFFING]
[GROWLING]
[IN BLACK SPEECH]
[DWARVES SNORING]
Where do you think you're going?
Back to Rivendell.
No, no, you can't turn back now, eh?
You're part of the company.
You're one of us.
I'm not, though, am I?
Thorin said I should never have come
and he was right.
I'm not a Took, I'm a Baggins.
I don't know what I was thinking.
-I should never have run out my door.
-You're homesick. I understand.
No, you don't. You don't understand.
None of you do.
You're Dwarves.
You're used to this life.
To living on the road, never settling
in one place, not belonging anywhere!
Oh, I am sorry. I didn't--
[CLEARS THROAT]
No, you're right.
We don't belong anywhere.
I wish you all the luck in the world.
I really do.
What's that?
BILBO:
Hmm?
Wake up! Wake up!
Whoa!
[ALL GRUNTING AND SCREAMING]
Look out! Look out!
DORI:
Get away!
[GOBLINS GROWLING]
GLOIN:
Filthy scum!
DWALIN:
Get back!
GLOIN:
You'll pay for this!
Got you.
DORI:
All right, all right. Don't push.
DWALIN: Get off! Get your hands off me!
Get off me!
[GOBLINS GROWLING]
[BILBO GASPS THEN GOBLIN GROWLS]
[BILBO YELLING]
[GOBLINS GROWLING]
Who would be so bold
as to come armed into my kingdom?
Spies? Thieves? Assassins?
Dwarves, Your Malevolence.
Dwarves?
We found them on the Front Porch.
Well, don't just stand there. Search them.
Every crack. Every crevice.
What are you doing in these parts?
Speak!
Very well. If they will not talk,
we'll make them squawk.
Bring up the mangler.
Bring up the bonebreaker.
-Start with the youngest.
THORIN: Wait!
Well, well, well.
Look who it is.
Thorin, son of Thrain, son of Thror...
...King Under the Mountain.
Oh, but I'm forgetting.
You don't have a mountain.
And you're not a king...
...which makes you nobody, really.
I know someone who would
pay a pretty price for your head.
Just a head.
Nothing attached.
Perhaps you know of whom I speak.
An old enemy of yours.
A pale Orc, astride a white Warg.
Azog the Defiler was destroyed.
He was slain in battle long ago.
So you think his defiling days are done,
do you?
[CHUCKLING]
Send word to the pale Orc.
Tell him I have found his prize.
[LAUGHING]
[RUSTLING]
Yes!
Yes.
Gollum, gollum!
[GOBLIN GROWLING]
Aah!
Nasty Goblinses!
Better than old bones, precious.
Better than nothing.
[GOLLUM WHIMPERS]
GOLLUM: Too many boneses, precious.
Not enough flesh!
Shut up! Cut its skin off.
Start with its head.
[GOLLUM GROANING]
[SINGING] The cold hard lands
They bites our hands
They gnaws our feet
The rocks and stones
They're like old bones
All bare of meat
Cold as death
Without no breath
It's good to eat
[GOBLIN SCREAMS]
Bless us and splash us, precious.
That's a meaty mouthful.
Gollum, gollum! Aah.
Back. Stay back.
I'm warning you, don't come any closer.
It's got an Elfish blade.
But it's not an Elfs.
Not an Elfs, no.
What is it, precious?
What is it?
My name is Bilbo Baggins.
Bagginses?
What is a Bagginses, precious?
-I'm a Hobbit from the Shire.
-Oh.
We like Goblinses, batses and fishes.
But we hasn't tried Hobbitses before.
ls it soft? ls it juicy?
Now, now, keep your distance!
I'll use this if I have to.
Aah!
I don't want any trouble,
do you understand?
Just show me the way to get out of here
and I'll be on my way.
Why? ls it lost?
Yes. Yes, and I want to get unlost
as soon as possible.
Ooh, we knows!
We knows safe paths for Hobbitses.
Safe paths in the dark.
Shut up!
-I didn't say anything.
-We wasn't talking to you.
Oh, yes, we was, precious. We was.
Look, I don't know what your game is,
but I--
Games?!
Oh, we love games,
doesn't we, precious?
Does it like games? Does it, does it?
Does it like to play?
Maybe.
What has roots as nobody sees?
ls taller than trees?
Up, up, up it goes
And yet, never grows
-The mountain.
-Yes, yes.
Oh, let's have another one, eh?
Yes! Do it again, do it again. Ask us.
No! No more riddles.
Finish him off. Finish him now!
Gollum, gollum!
No! No. No.
No. I want to play. I do.
I want to play. I can see...
...you are very good at this.
So why don't we...
...have a game of riddles? Yes?
Just you and me.
Yes. Yes, just us.
Yes. Yes.
And if I win...
...you show me the way out. Yes?
Yes. Yes.
And if it loses? What then?
Well, if it loses, precious,
then we eats it!
If Baggins loses, we eats it whole.
Fair enough.
Well, Baggins first.
Thirty white horses on a red hill
First they champ, then they stamp
Then they stand still
Teeth?
Teeth! Oh, yes, my precious!
But we-- We only have nine.
Our turn.
Voiceless, it cries
Wingless flutters
Toothless bites
Mouthless mutters
Just a minute. Uh....
Oh. Oh!
We knows! We knows!
Shut up!
Wind.
It's wind. Of course it is.
Very clever, Hobbitses.
Very clever.
Ah-ah-ah.
A box without hinges, key or lid
Yet golden treasure inside is hid
Box.
Oh, um....
Box. The lid and a key.
-Well?
-It's nasty.
-Box. Key.
-Do you give up?
Give us a chance, precious!
Give us a chance!
[GRUNTING]
Eggses!
Wet, crunchy little eggses. Yes.
Grandmother taught us
to suck them, yes!
[WINGS FLUTTERING]
[GOLLUM EXHALES]
GOLLUM:
We have one for you.
All things it devours
Birds, beasts, trees, flowers
Gnaws iron, bites steel
Grinds hard stones to meal
Answer us.
Give me a moment, please.
I gave you a good long while.
Birds, beasts.... Beasts?
Trees, flowers.
I don't know this one.
GOLLUM:
ls it tasty?
ls it scrumptious?
ls it crunchable?
Let me think.
It's stuck.
Bagginses is stuck.
Time's up.
Time.
The answer is time.
[GROWLING]
Actually it wasn't that hard.
Last question.
Last chance.
BILBO:
Okay.
Ask us.
-Ask us!
-Yes, yes. All right.
What have I got in my pocket?
That's no fair.
It's not fair! It's against the rules!
Now ask us another one.
No. No, no, no.
You said ask me a question.
Well, that is my question.
What have I got in my pocket?
[GROANS]
Three guesses, precious.
lt must give us three!
Three guesses. Very well, guess away.
Handses!
Wrong. Guess again.
[GRUNTS]
Fishbones, Goblins' teeth,
wet shells, bats' wings....
[GRUNTING]
Knife! Oh, shut up!
Wrong again. Last guess.
String. Or nothing.
Two guesses at once.
Wrong both times.
[SOBBING]
BILBO:
So....
Come, then. I won the game.
You promised to show me the way out.
GOLLUM:
Did we say so, precious?
Did we say so?
What has it got in its pocketses?
That's no concern of yours.
You lost.
Lost?
Where is it?
Where is it?!
No!
[SCREAMS]
Where is it?!
No! No!
Lost!
Curse us and splash us!
My precious is lost!
-What have you lost?
-Mustn't ask us! Not its business!
No!
Gollum, gollum!
[PANTING]
What has it got...
...in its nasty...
...little pocketses?
He stole it.
He stole it!
[SCREAMS]
GREAT GOBLIN [SINGING]:
Bones will be shattered
Necks will be wrung
You'll be beaten and battered
From racks you'll be hung
You will die down here
And never be found
Down in the deep of Goblin-town
I know that sword!
lt is the Goblin-cleaver!
The Biter!
The blade that sliced 1 000 necks!
Slash them! Beat them! Kill them!
Kill them all!
Cut off his head!
Take up arms.
Fight.
Fight!
[ALL GRUNTING]
He wields the Foehammer! The Beater!
Bright as daylight!
NORI:
Thorin!
[WHIMPERING]
Follow me. Quick!
Run!
[GOLLUM GRUNTING NEARBY]
GOLLUM:
Give it to us!
[GRUNTING]
[GOLLUM GROWLING]
It's ours.
It's ours!
[SCREAMS]
Thief!
Baggins!
GANDALF:
Quickly!
DORI:
Faster!
[GOBLINS GROWLING]
DWALIN:
Post!
Charge!
Cut the ropes!
GANDALF:
Come on, quickly!
DWALIN: Come on, move!
FILI: Bombur!
BOMBUR:
Go, go, go!
THORIN:
Jump!
OIN:
Jump, lad!
GANDALF:
Come on!
DWALIN:
Push!
DORI:
Come on!
GLOIN: Watch your backs!
-You thought you could escape me.
What are you going to do now, Wizard?
[GROANING]
That'll do it.
[ALL SCREAMING]
[ALL GROANING]
BOFUR:
Well, that could have been worse.
DWALIN:
Haver!
You've got to be joking!
Gandalf!
[GOBLINS GROWLING]
There's too many. We can't fight them.
Only one thing will save us, daylight!
Come on! Here! On your feet.
OIN: Balin.
DWALIN: Come on!
[GRUNTS]
Wait!
My precious. Wait!
Gollum, gollum!
[FOOTSTEPS]
GANDALF:
Quick, quick!
This way.
[GASPS]
DORI: Come on.
GANDALF: Come on, come on. Quickly.
Right, good!
[SCREAMS]
Baggins!
Thief!
Curse it and crush it!
We hates it forever!
Five, six, seven, eight.
Bifur. Bofur. That's 1 0.
Fili, Kili! That's 12.
And Bombur. That makes 1 3.
Where's Bilbo?
Where is our Hobbit?
DWALIN:
Curse that Halfling! Now he's lost?
GLOIN:
I thought he was with Dori!
-Don't blame me!
-Well, where did you last see him?
I think I saw him slip away
when they first collared us.
GANDALF:
And what happened, exactly?
-Tell me!
-I'll tell you what happened.
Master Baggins saw his chance
and he took it.
He has thought of nothing
but his soft bed and his warm hearth...
...since first he stepped out of his door.
We will not be seeing our Hobbit again.
He is long gone.
No. He isn't.
Bilbo Baggins.
I have never been so glad
to see anyone in my life.
Bilbo. We'd given you up.
How on earth
did you get past the Goblins?
How, indeed.
[CHUCKLES]
Well, what does it matter? He's back.
lt matters. I want to know.
Why did you come back?
Look, I know you doubt me.
I know you always have.
And you're right, I often think of Bag-end.
I miss my books.
And my armchair and my garden.
See, that's where I belong.
That's home.
And that's why I came back. Because...
...you don't have one. A home.
lt was taken from you.
But I will help you take it back if I can.
[GROWLING]
[IN BLACK SPEECH]
Out of the frying pan.
And into the fire. Run.
Run!
[WARGS HOWLING]
[GROWLING]
THORIN:
Go!
Up into the trees!
All of you! Come on, climb! Bilbo, climb!
THORIN:
Quickly!
[GRUNTS]
THORIN:
They're coming!
[DWARVES YELLING]
BOFUR: Hang on!
GLOIN: Hold on, brothers!
[WHISPERS INDISTINCTLY]
[GROWLING]
Azog.
[SNIFFING]
[IN BLACK SPEECH]
lt cannot be.
[DWARVES SCREAMING]
[WARGS BARKING AND GROWLING]
DWALIN:
It's going!
[DWARVES SCREAMING]
[LAUGHS]
GANDALF:
Fili!
[DWARVES YELLING]
[ROARS]
Yeah!
[ALL LAUGHING]
GANDALF:
No!
[GASPS THEN SCREAMS]
Oh, no.
Mr. Gandalf!
ORI:
Oh, no, Dori!
[GROWLING]
[GRUNTS]
[ROARS]
ORI:
Help!
[AZOG YELLS]
No!
[GROWLS]
[SCREAMING]
Thorin! No!
[GRUNTS]
[IN BLACK SPEECH]
[BILBO YELLS]
[WARGS GROWLING]
[DWARVES YELLING]
[YELLS]
[SCREAMING]
[EAGLES SQUAWKING]
[ROARING]
Look.
[BILBO SCREAMING]
[ROARING]
Thorin!
GANDALF:
Thorin.
[GANDALF WHISPERING INDISTINCTLY]
The Halfling?
It's all right.
Bilbo is here. He's quite safe.
[SIGHS]
You!
What were you doing?
You nearly got yourself killed!
Did I not say that
you would be a burden?
That you would not survive in the Wild?
That you had no place amongst us?
I have never been so wrong in all my life.
[ALL CHEERING AND LAUGHING]
But I'm sorry I doubted you.
No, I would have doubted me too.
I'm not a hero or a warrior.
Not even a burglar.
[EAGLE SQUAWKS]
ls that what I think it is?
GANDALF:
Erebor...
...the Lonely Mountain...
...the last of the great Dwarf kingdoms
of Middle-earth.
Our home.
[BIRD CHIRPING]
OIN:
A raven!
The birds are returning to the mountain.
That, my dear Oin, is a thrush.
But we'll take it as a sign.
-A good omen.
-You're right.
I do believe the worst is behind us.
[GROWLING]
NEIL FINN [SINGING]:
Far over the misty mountains rise
Leave us standing upon the height
What was before
We see once more
ls our kingdom a distant light
Fiery mountain beneath the moon
The words unspoken, we'll be there soon
For home a song
That echoes on
And all who find us will know the tune
Some folk we never forget
Some kind we never forgive
Haven't seen the back of us yet
We'll fight as long as we live
All eyes on the hidden door
To the Lonely Mountain borne
We'll ride in the gathering storm
Until we get our long-forgotten gold
We lay under the misty mountains cold
ln slumbers deep
And dreams of gold
We must awake
Our lives to make
And in the darkness a torch we hold
From long ago when lanterns burned
Until this day
Our hearts have yearned
Her fate unknown
The Arkenstone
What was stolen
Must be returned
We must awake
And make the day
To find a song for heart and soul
Some folk we never forget
Some kind we never forgive
Haven't seen the end of it yet
We'll fight as long as we live
All eyes on the hidden door
To the Lonely Mountain borne
We'll ride in the gathering storm
Till we get our long-forgotten gold
Far away from misty mountains cold